<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The discovery of a world in the moone, or, A discourse tending to prove, that 'tis probable there may be another habitable world in that planet</title>
            <author>Wilkins, John, 1614-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 212 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 112 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25640</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2974</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29616684</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29616684</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28034</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15363)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28034)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1860:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The discovery of a world in the moone, or, A discourse tending to prove, that 'tis probable there may be another habitable world in that planet</title>
                  <author>Wilkins, John, 1614-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 209, [4] p. illus., diagrs.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E. G. for Michael Sparke and Edward Forrest,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London,</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Wilkins by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴, B-O⁸, P⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astronomy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Moon --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:28034:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of solar system and planetary orbits</figDesc>
                  <head>THE DISCOVERY OF A VVORLD IN THE MOONE.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Saturnus ♄</item>
                        <item>Jupiter ♃</item>
                        <item>Mars ♂</item>
                        <item>Ceres et Proſerpina <g ref="char:Moonnew">●</g> 
                           <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>
                        </item>
                        <item>Venus ♀</item>
                        <item>Mercu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s ☿</item>
                     </list> Sua fovent<lb/>Mutuo ſe illuminant<lb/>Vniuerſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ornant</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>☉</speaker>
                     <p>Ame omnes</p>
                  </sp>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28034:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> OR, A DISCOVRSE Tending, TO PROVE, that 'tis probable there may be another habitable World in that Planet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quid tibi inquis iſta proderunt? Si nihil aliud, hoc certè, ſciam omnia anguſta eſſe.</hi> SENECA. Praef. ad 1. Lib. <hi>N. Q.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>E. G.</hi> for <hi>Michael Sparke</hi> and <hi>Edward Forreſt,</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:28034:2"/>
            <p>Perlegi haec <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; novitatis gratiâ ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis mandari per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitto.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Mart.</hi> 29. 1638.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>THO. WEEKES</hi> R. P. Epiſc. Lond. Cap. Domeſt.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:28034:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F amongſt thy leiſure houres thou canſt ſpare any for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſall of this diſcourſe, and doſt looke to find ſomewhat in it which may ſerve for thy information and benefit: let me then adviſe thee to come unto it with an equall minde, not ſwayed by prejudice, but indifferently reſolved to aſſent unto that truth which upon deliberation ſhall ſeeme moſt probable unto thy reaſon, and then I doubt not, but either thou wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> agree with mee in this aſſertion, or at leaſt not thinke it to be as farre from truth, as it is from common opinion.</p>
            <p>Two cautions th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re are which I would willingly admoniſh thee of in the beginning.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:28034:3"/> 1. That thou ſhouldſt not here looke to find any exact, accurate Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, ſince this diſcourſe was but the fruit of ſome lighter ſtudies, and thoſe too hudled up in a ſhort time, being firſt thought of and finiſhed in the ſpace of ſome few weekes, and therefore you cannot in reaſon expect, that it ſhould be ſo poliſhed, as perhaps, the ſubject would require, or the leiſure of the Author might have done it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To remember that I promiſe onely probable arguments for the proofe of this opinion, and therefore you muſt not looke that every conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſhould be of an undeniable dependance, or that the truth of each argument ſhould be meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by its neceſſity. I grant that ſome Aſtronomicall appearances may poſſibly be ſolved otherwiſe then here they are. But the thing I aime at is this, that probably they may ſo be ſolved, as I have here ſet them downe: Which, if it be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as I thinke it muſt) then I
<pb facs="tcp:28034:3"/> doubt not, but the indifferent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will find ſome ſatisfaction in the maine thing that is to be proved.</p>
            <p>Many ancient Philoſophers of the better note, have formerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended this aſſertion, which I have here laid downe, and it were to be wiſhed, that ſome of us would more apply our endeavours unto the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of theſe old opinions, which though they have for a long time lien neglected by others, yet in them may you finde many truths well worthy your paines and obſervation. Tis a falſe conceit, for us to thinke, that amongſt the ancient variety and ſearch of opinions, the beſt hath ſtill prevailed. Time (ſaith the learned <hi>Verulam)</hi> ſeemes to be of the nature of a river or ſtreame, which carrieth downe to us that which is light, or blowne up, but ſinketh that which is weighty and ſolid.</p>
            <p>It is my deſire that by the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this diſcourſe, I may raiſe up ſome more active ſpirit to a ſearch
<pb facs="tcp:28034:4"/> after other hidden and unknowne truths. Since it muſt needes be a great impediment unto the growth of ſciences, for men ſtill ſo to plod on upon beaten principles, as to be afraid of entertaining any thing that may ſeeme to contradict them. An un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe to take ſuch things into examination, is one of thoſe errours of learning in theſe times obſerved by the judicious <hi>Verulam.</hi> Queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there are many ſecret truths, which the ancients have paſſed over, that are yet left to make ſome of our age famous for their diſcovery.</p>
            <p>If by this occaſion I may provoke any reader to an attempt of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, I ſhall then thinke my ſelfe happy, and this worke ſucceſſefull.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="book">
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:28034:4"/>
               <head>The Firſt Propoſition, by way of Preface. <hi>That the ſtrangeneſſe of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is no ſufficient reaſon why it ſhould be rejected, -becauſe other certaine truths have beene formerly eſteemed ridiculous, and great abſurdities entertayned by common conſent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is an earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and hunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after noveltie, which doth ſtill adhere unto all our natures, and it is part of that primitive image, that wide ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and infinite capacity at firſt created in the heart of man, for this ſince its depravation in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:28034:5"/> 
                  <hi>Adam</hi> perceiving it ſelfe altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther emptied of any good doth now catch after every new thing, conceiving that poſſibly it may finde ſatisfaction among ſome of its fellow creatures. But our enemy the divell (who ſtrives ſtill to pervert our gifts, and beate us with our owne wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons) hath ſo contriv'd it, that any truth doth now ſeeme diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtefull for that very reaſon, for which errour is entertain'd—Novelty, for let but ſome up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart hereſie be ſet abroach, and preſently there are ſome out of a curious humour; others, as if they watched an occaſion of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, will take it up for ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, and make it part of their creede and profeſſion;-whereas ſolitary truth cannot any where finde ſo ready enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement; but the ſame Novelty which is eſteemed the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of errour and makes that acceptable, is counted the fault
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:28034:5"/> of truth, and cauſes that to bee rejected. How did the incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous World gaze at <hi>Columbus</hi> when he promiſed to diſcover another part of the earth, and he could not for a long time by his confidence, or arguments, induce any of the Chriſtian Princes, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to aſſent unto his opinion, or goe to the charges of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment. Now if he who had ſuch good grounds for his aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could finde no better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement among the wiſer ſort, and upper end of the World; 'tis not likely then that this opinion which I now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhall receive any thing from the men of theſe daies, eſpecially our vulgar wits, but misbeliefe or deriſion. It hath alwaies beene the unhappineſſe of new truths in Philoſophy, to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided by thoſe that are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the cauſes of things, and reiected by others whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe ties them to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:28034:6"/> opinion, men whoſe envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pride will not allow any new thing for truth which they themſelves were not the firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventors of. So that I may iuſtly expect to be accuſed of a prag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall ignorance, and bold oſtentation, eſpecially ſince for this opinion <hi>Xenophanes,</hi> a man whoſe authority was able to adde ſome credit to his aſſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could not eſcape the like cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from others. For <hi>Natales</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mytholog. lib. 3. c. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Comes</hi> ſpeaking of that Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, and this his opinion, ſaith thus, <hi>Nonnulli ne nihil ſciſſe videantur, aliqua novo monſtra in Philoſophia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> introducunt, ut alicuius rei inventores fuiſſe appareant.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Some there are who leaſt they might ſeeme to know nothing, will bring up monſtrous abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in Philoſophy, that ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward they may bee famed for the invention of ſomewhat.</q> The ſame author doth alſo in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place accuſe <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 7. c. 1.</note>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:28034:6"/> of folly for the ſame opinion, <hi>Eſt enim non ignobilis gradus ſtul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiae, vel ſi neſcias quid dicas, tamen velle de rebus propoſitis hanc vel illam partem ſtabilire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">'Tis none of the worſt kindes of folly, boldly to affirme one ſide or other, when a man knows not what to ſay.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe men were thus cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd, I may iuſtly then expect to be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ided by moſt, and to be believed by few or none; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſince this opinion ſeemes to carry in it ſo much ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo much contradiction to the generall conſent of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But how ever, I am reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that this ſhall not be any diſcouragement, ſince I know that it is not the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of others that can either adde or detract from the truth. For,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Other truths have beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly eſteemed altogether as ridiculous as this can be.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:28034:7"/> 2 Groſſe abſurdities have beene entertained by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall opinion.</p>
               <p>I ſhall give an inſtance of each, that ſo I may the better prepare the Reader to conſider things without a prejudice, when hee ſhall ſee that the common op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt this which I affirme cannot any way dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from its truth.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Other truths have beene formerly accounted as ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as this, I ſhall ſpecifie that of the Antipodes, which have beene denied and laught at by many wiſe men and great Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, ſuch as were <hi>Herodotus,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtine, Lactantius,</hi> the <hi>Venerable Bede, Lucretius</hi> the Poet, <hi>Procopi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the voluminous <hi>Abulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> with others. <hi>Herodotus</hi> coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſo horrible an abſurdity, that hee could not forbeare laughing to thinke of it. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:28034:7"/> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <q rend="margQuotes">I cannot chooſe but laugh, (ſaith he) to ſee ſo many men venture to deſcribe the earths compaſſe, relating thoſe things that are without all ſenſe, as that the Sea flowes about the World, and that the earth it ſelfe is round as an Orbe.</q> But this great ignorance is not ſo much to be admired in him, as in thoſe learneder men of later times, when all ſciences began to flouriſh in the World. Such was Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> who cenſures that relation of the Antipodes to be an incredible fable, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>de Civit. Dei. lib.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note> with him agrees the eloquent <hi>Lactantius, quid illi qui eſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarios veſtigiis noſtris Antipodes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtitut. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>putant? num aliquid loquuntur? aut eſt quiſpiam tam ineptus, qui credat eſſe homines, quorum veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia ſunt ſuperiora quàm capita? aut ibi quae apud nos jacent inver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:28034:8"/> 
                  <hi>pendere? fruges &amp; arbores deor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum verſus creſcere, pluvias &amp; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves, &amp; grandinem ſurſum verſus cadere in terram? &amp; miratur aliquis ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tos penſiles inter ſeptem mira narrari, quum Philoſophi, &amp; agros &amp; maria, &amp; urbes &amp; montes penſiles faciunt? &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">What (ſaith he) are they that thinke there are Antipodes, ſuch as walke with their feete againſt ours? doe they ſpeake any likely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood? or is there any one ſo fooliſh as to believe that there are men whoſe heeles are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than their heads? that things which with us doe lie on the ground doe hang there? that the Plants and Trees grow downewards, that the haile, and raine, and ſnow fall upwards to the earth? and doe wee admire the hanging Orchards amongſt the ſeven wonders, whereas here the Philoſophers have made the Field and Seas, the Cities and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28034:8"/> mountaines hanging.</q> What ſhall wee thinke (ſaith hee in <hi>Plutareh)</hi> that men doe clyng to that place like wormes, or hang by their clawes as Cats, or if wee ſuppoſe a man a little beyond the Center, to be dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging with a ſpade? is it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (as it muſt be according to this opinion) that the earth which hee looſened, ſhould of it ſelfe aſcend upwards? or elſe ſuppoſe two men with their middles about the center, the feete of the one being placed where the head of the other is, and ſo two other men croſſe them, yet all theſe men thus ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuated according to this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhould ſtand upright, and many other ſuch groſſe conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences would follow (ſaith he) which a falſe imagination is not able to fancy as poſſible. Vpon which conſiderations, <hi>Bede</hi> alſo denies the being of any <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De ratione temporum, Cap</hi> 32.</note> Antipodes, <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim Antipoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:28034:9"/> 
                  <hi>ullatenus eſt Fabulls accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modandus aſſenſus,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Nor ſhould wee any longer aſſent to the Fable of Antipodes.</q> So alſo <hi>Lucretius</hi> the Poet ſpeaking of the ſame ſubject, ſaies,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Sedvanus ſtolidis haec omnia finxerit error.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Denat. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, Lib.</hi> 1.</note>
               </q>
               <p>That ſome idle fancy faigned theſe for fooles to believe. Of this opinion was <hi>Procopius Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaeus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comment. in</hi> 1. <hi>Cap. Gen.</hi>
                  </note> but he was perſwaded to it by another kinde of reaſon; for he thought that all the earth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us was ſunke in the water, according to the ſaying of the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Hee hath founded the <note place="margin">Pſal. 24. 2.</note> earth upon the Seas, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he accounted it not inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any. Nay <hi>Toſtatus</hi> a man of later yeeres and generall lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning doth alſo confidently deny that there are any ſuch Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, though the reaſon which he urges for it be not ſo abſurd as the former, for the Apoſtles, ſaith he, travelled through the whole <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comment. in</hi> 1. Geneſ.</note>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:28034:9"/> habitable world, but they never paſſed the Equinoctiall; and if you anſwer that they are ſaid to goe through all the earth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they went through all the knowne world, hee replies, that this is not ſufficient, ſince Chriſt would have all men to be ſaved, and come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his truth, and therefore <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 4.</note> 'tis requiſite that they ſhould have travelled thither alſo, if there had been any inhabitants, eſpecially ſince he did expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly command them to goe and teach all nations, and preach the Goſpell through the whole <note place="margin">Mat. 28. 19.</note> world, and therefore he thinkes that as there are no men, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are there ſeas, or rivers, or any other conveniency for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation: 'tis commonly related of one <hi>Virgilius,</hi> that he was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated and condemned for a Heretique by <hi>Zachary</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe hee was not of the ſame opinion. But
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:28034:10"/> 
                  <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaies, it was becauſe hee <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Annal. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. A. D.</hi> 748.</note> thought there was another ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable world within ours. How ever, you may well enough diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne in theſe examples how confident many of theſe great Schollars were in ſo groſſe an errour, how unlikely, what an incredible thing it ſeemed to them, that there ſhould be any Antipodes, and yet now this truth is as certaine and plaine, as ſenſe or demonſtration can make it. This then which I now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is not to be rejected, though it may ſeeme to contradict the common opinion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Groſſe abſurdities have beene entertained by generall conſent. I might inſtance in many remarkeable examples, but I will onely ſpeake of the ſuppoſed labour of the Moone in her eclipſes, becauſe this is neereſt to the chiefe matter in hand, and was received as a common opinion amongſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:28034:10"/> of the ancients, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaking of a Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary eclipſe, relates, that at ſuch times 'twas a cuſtome amongſt the <hi>Romanes</hi> (the moſt civill and learned people in the world) to ſound braſſe Inſtruments, and <note place="margin">In vita Paul. Aemil.</note> hold great torches toward the heaven. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. for by this meanes they ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Moone was much eaſed in her labours, and therfore <hi>Ovid</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Metam. Lib.</hi> 4.</note> calls ſuch loud Inſtruments the auxiliaries or helpes of the Moone
<q>Cum fruſtra reſonant aera auxiliaria Lunae.</q> and therefore the Satyriſt too deſcribing a loud ſcold, ſaies, ſhe was able to make noiſe enough to deliver the labouring Moone.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Vna laboranti poterit ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ccurrere Lunae.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iuven. Sat.</hi> 6</note>
               </q>
               <p>Now the reaſon of all this their ceremonie, was, becauſe they feared the world would fall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:28034:11"/> aſleepe, when one of its eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to wincke, and therefore they would doe what they could by loud ſounds to rouſe it from its drowſineſſe, and keepe it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake by bright torches, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow that light upon it which it beganne to loſe. Some of them thought hereby to keepe the Moone in her orbe, whereas otherwiſe ſhe would have fallen downe upon the earth, and the world would have loſt one of its lights, for the credulous people believed, that Inchanters and Witches could bring the Moone downe, which made <hi>Virgil</hi> ſay,
<q>Can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us &amp; è coelo poſſunt deducere Lunam.</q> And thoſe Wizards knowing the times of her eclipſes, would then threaten to ſhew their skill, by pulling her out of her orbe. So that when the ſilly multitude ſaw that ſhe began to looke red, they preſently feared they ſhould loſe the benefit of her light, and therefore made a great noiſe that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:28034:11"/> ſhe might not heare the ſound of thoſe Charmes, which would otherwiſe bring her downe, and this is rendred for a reaſon of this cuſtome by <hi>Pliny</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertius:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. Hiſt. Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Cantus &amp; è curru lunam deducere tentant,</l>
                  <l>Et facerent, ſi non aera repulſaſonent.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> gives another reaſon of it, and he ſaies, 'tis becauſe they would haſten the Moone out of the darke ſhade wherein ſhe was involv'd, that ſo ſhe might bring away the ſoules of thoſe Saints that inhabit within her, which cry out by reaſon they are then deprived of their wonted happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and cannot heare the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke of the Spheares, but are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to behold the torments, and wailing of thoſe damned ſoules which are repreſented to them as they are tortured in the region of the aire, but whether this or what ever elſe was the meaning of this ſuperſtition, yet certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly 'twas a very ridiculous cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:28034:12"/> and bewrayed a great ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of thoſe ancient times, eſpecially ſince it was not onely received by the vulgar, ſuch as were men of leſſe note and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but believed alſo, by the more famous and wiſer ſort, ſuch as were thoſe great Poets, <hi>Steſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorus</hi> and <hi>Pindar.</hi> And not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amongſt the more ſottiſh hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, who might account that Planet to be one of their Gods, but the primitive Chriſtians al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo were in this kinde guilty, which made S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſo tartly to rebuke thoſe of his time, when he ſaid, <hi>Tum turbatur car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus Globus Lunae, quando ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licibus turbantur &amp; oculi.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">When your heads are troubled with cups, then you thinke the Moone to be troubled with charmes.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And for this reaſon alſo did <hi>Maximus</hi> a Biſhop, write a <note place="margin">Turinenſ. Epiſc.</note> Homily againſt it, wherein hee ſhewed the abſurditie of that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:28034:12"/> fooliſh ſuperſtition. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that <hi>Ludovicus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ives</hi> relates a more ridiculous ſtory of a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that impriſoned an Aſſe for drinking up the Moone, whoſe image appearing in the water was covered with a cloud as the Aſſe was drinking, for which the poore beaſt was afterward brought to the barre to receive a ſentence according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, where the grave Senate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet to examine the matter, one of the Counſell (perhaps wiſer than the reſt) riſes up, and out of his deepe judgement thinkes it not fit that their Towne ſhould loſe its Moone, but that rather the Aſſe ſhould bee cut up and that taken out of him, which ſentence being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the reſt of thoſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticians, as the ſubtilleſt way for the concluſion of the matter was accordingly performed. But whether this tale were true or no I will not queſtion, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:28034:13"/> there is abſurdity enough in that former cuſtome of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients that may confirme the truth to be proved, and plainely declare the inſufficiency of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon opinion to adde true worth or eſtimation unto any thing. So that from that which I have ſaid may be gathered thus much.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That a new truth may ſeeme abſurd and impoſſible not onely to the vulgar, but to thoſe alſo who are otherwiſe wiſe men and excellent ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; and hence it will follow that every new thing which ſeemes to oppoſe common principles is not preſently to bee rejected, but rather to bee pry'd into with a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent enquiry, ſince there are many things which are yet hid from us, and reſerv'd for future diſcovery.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That it is not the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an opinion that can priviledge it for a truth, the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:28034:13"/> wrong way is ſometime a well beaten path, whereas the right way (eſpecially to hidden truths) may be leſſe trodden and more obſcure.</p>
               <p>True indeed, the ſtrangeneſſe of this opinion will detract much from its credit; but yet we ſhould know that nothing is in its ſelfe ſtrange, ſince every naturall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect has an equall dependance upon its cauſe, and with the like neceſſity doth follow from it, ſo that 'tis our ignorance which makes things appeare ſo, and hence it comes to paſſe that many more evident truths ſeeme incredible to ſuch who know not the cauſes of things: you may as ſoone perſwade ſome Countrey peaſants that the Moone is made of greene Cheeſe (as we ſay) as that 'tis bigger than his Cart-wheele ſince both ſeeme equally to contradict his ſight, and he has not reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to leade him farther than
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:28034:14"/> his ſenſes. Nay ſuppoſe (ſaith <hi>Plutarch)</hi> a Philoſopher ſhould bee educated in ſuch a ſecret place, where hee might not ſee either Sea or River and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſhould bee brought out where one might ſhew him the great Ocean telling him the quality of that water that it is brackiſh ſalt and not potable, and yet there were many vaſt creatures of all formes living in it, which make uſe of the water as we doe of the ayre, queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he would laugh at al this as being monſtrous lies, and fables without any colour of truth. Juſt ſo will this truth which I now deliver appeare unto others; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we never dreamt of any ſuch matter as a world in the Moone, becauſe the ſtate of that place hath as yet beene vailed from our knowledge, therefore we can ſcarcely aſſent to any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Things are very hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived which are altogether
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:28034:14"/> ſtrange to our thoughts and our ſenſes. The ſoule may with leſſe difficulty be brought to believe any abſurdity, when as it has formerly beene acquainted with ſome colours and probabilities for it, but when a new, and an unheard of truth ſhall come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it, though it have good grounds and reaſons, yet the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding is afraid of it as a ſtranger, and dares not admit it into its beliefe without a great deale of reluctanty and tryall. And beſides things that are not manifeſted to the ſenſes, are not aſſented unto without ſome la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of mind, ſome travaile and diſcourſe of the underſtanding, and many lazie ſoules had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quietly repoſe themſelves in an eaſie errour, then take paines to ſearch out the truth. The ſtrangeneſſe then of this opinion which I now deliver will be a great hinderance to its beliefe, but this is not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:28034:15"/> by reaſon it cannot bee helped. I have ſtood the longer in the Preface, becauſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice which the meere title of the booke may beget cannot ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily be removed without a great deale of preparation, and I could not tell otherwiſe how to recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the thoughts of the reader for an impartiall ſurvey of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>I muſt needs confeſſe, though I had often thought with my ſelfe that it was poſſible there might be a world in the Moone, yet it ſeemed ſuch an uncouth opinion that I never durſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it, for feare of being coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſingular and ridiculous, but afterward having read <hi>Plutarch, Galileus, Keplar,</hi> with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and finding many of mine owne thoughts confirmed by ſuch ſtrong authority, I then concluded that it was not onely poſſible there might be, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that there was another
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:28034:15"/> habitable world in that Planet. In the proſecuting of this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſhall firſt endeavour to cleare the way from ſuch doubts as may hinder the ſpeed or eaſe of farther progreſſe; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſuppoſitions imply'd in this opinion may ſeeme to contradict the principles of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or faith, it will be requiſite that I firſt remove this ſcruple ſhewing the conformity of them to both theſe, and proving thoſe truths that may make way for the reſt, which I ſhall labour to performe in the ſecond, third, fourth, and fifth Chapters, and then proceede to confirme ſuch propoſitions, which doe more directly belong to the maine point in hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:28034:16"/>
               <head>Propoſition 2. <hi>That a plurality of worlds doth not contradict any principle of reaſon or faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TIs reported of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> that when hee ſaw the bookes of <hi>Moſes</hi> he commended them for ſuch a majeſticke ſtile as might become a God, but withall hee cenſured that manner of writing to be very unfitting for a Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher becauſe there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing proved in them, but mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were delivered as if they would rather command than perſwade beliefe. And 'tis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that hee ſets downe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing himſelfe, but he confirmes it by the ſtrongeſt reaſons that may be found, there being ſcarce an argument of force for any ſubject in Philoſophy which may not bee picked out of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:28034:16"/> his writings, and therefore 'tis likely if there were in reaſon a neceſſity of one onely world, that hee would have found out ſome ſuch neceſſary proofe as might confirme it: Eſpecially ſince hee labours for it ſo much in two whole Chapters. But now all the arguments which he himſelfe urges in this ſubject, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Coelo l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. 9.</note> are very weake and farre enough from having in them any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing power. Therefore 'tis likely that a plurality of worlds doth not contradict any princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of reaſon. However, I will ſet downe the two chiefe of his arguments from his owne workes, and from them you may gueſſe the force of the other. The 1 is this, ſince every heavy <note place="margin">ibid.</note> body doth naturally tend down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and every light body up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, what a hudling and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion muſt there bee if there were two places for gravity and two places for lightneſſe: for it
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:28034:17"/> is probable that the earth of that other world would fall downe to this Centre, and ſo mutually the aire and fire here aſcend to thoſe Regions in the other, which muſt needs much derogate from the providence of nature, and cauſe a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order in his workes. To this I anſwer, that if you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the nature of gravity, you will plainely ſee there is no ground to feare any ſuch confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, for heavineſſe is nothing elſe but ſuch a quality as cauſes a propenſion in 'its ſubject to tend downewards towards its owne Centre, ſo that for ſome of that earth to come hither would not bee ſaid a fall but an aſcenſion, ſince it moved from its owne place, and this would be impoſſible (ſaith <hi>Ruvio)</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe againſt nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no more to bee feared <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Coelo l.</hi> 1. <hi>c</hi> 9. <hi>q.</hi> 1.</note> than the falling of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:28034:17"/>
               <p> Another argument hee had <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Metaphyſ. l.</hi> 12. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Diog. Laert. lib.</hi> 3.</note> from his maſter <hi>Plato,</hi> that there is but one world, becauſe there is but one firſt mover, God.</p>
               <p>But here I may deny the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, ſince a plurality of worlds doth not take away the unity of the firſt mover. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t enim forma ſubſtantialis, ſic primum efficiens apparentem ſolummodo multiplicitatem induit per ſignatam</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nic. Hill. de Philoſop. Epic. partic.</hi> 379.</note> 
                  <hi>materiam</hi> (ſaith a Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of ours.) As the ſubſtantiall forme, ſo the efficient cauſe hath onely an appearing multiplicity from its particular matter. You may ſee this point more largely handled, and theſe Arguments more fully anſwered by <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> in his booke (why Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles are ſilent) and <hi>Iacob Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentarius</hi> in his comment on <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But our oppoſites the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters themſelves, (who too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten doe <hi>jurare in verba magiſtri)</hi> will grant that there is not any
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:28034:18"/> ſtrength in theſe conſequences, and certainely their ſuch weake arguments could not convince that wiſe Philoſopher, who in his other opinions was wont to bee ſwayed by the ſtrength and power of reaſon: wherefore I ſhould rather thinke that he had ſome by-reſpect, which made him firſt aſſent to this opinion, and afterwards ſtrive to prove it. Perhaps it was becauſe hee feared to diſpleaſe his ſcholler <hi>Alexander,</hi> of whom 'tis related <note place="margin">Plutarch. de tranq. anim.</note> that he wept to heare a diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another world, ſince he had not then attained the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of this, his reſtleſſe wide heart would have eſteemed this Globe of Earth not big enough for him, if there had beene ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which made the Satyriſt ſay of him,</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>Aeſtuat infoelix anguſto limite mundi.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iuvenal.</note>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That he did vexe himſelfe and ſweate in his deſires, as being pend up in a narrow roome,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:28034:18"/> when hee was confin'd but to one world.</q> Before he thought to ſeate himſelfe next the Gods, but now when hee had done his beſt, hee muſt be content with ſome equall, or perhaps ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Kings.</p>
               <p>It may be, that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was moved to this opinion, that hee might therby take from <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the occaſion of this feare and diſcontent, or elſe, perhaps, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe was as loth to hold the poſſibility of a world which he could not diſcover, as <hi>Alexander</hi> was to heare of one which hee could not conquer. Tis likely that ſome ſuch by-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect moved him to this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſince the arguments he urges for it are confeſt by his zealous followers and commentators, to be very ſleight and frivolous, and they themſelves grant, what I am now to prove, that there is not any evidence in the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſon, which can ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:28034:19"/> manifeſt that there is but one world.</p>
               <p>But however ſome may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, would it not be inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and dangerous to admit of ſuch opinions that doe deſtroy thoſe principles of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> which all the world hath ſo long followed?</p>
               <p>This queſtion is much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Divines; <note place="margin">Apologia pro Galilaeo.</note> 
                  <hi>Campanella</hi> hath writ a Treatiſe in defence of it, in whom you may ſee many things worth the reading and notice.</p>
               <p>To it I anſwer, that this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in Philoſophy, doth not bring any inconvenience to the reſt, ſince tis not <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> but truth that ſhould be the rule of our opinions, and if they be not both found together, wee may ſay to him, as hee ſaid to his <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ethic. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> Maſter <hi>Plato,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <q rend="margQuotes">Though <hi>Plato</hi> were his friend, yet hee would rather adhere to truth than him.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:28034:19"/>
               <p> I muſt needes grant, that wee are all much beholden to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry of the ancient Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, and more eſpecially to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> for the greater part of our learning, but yet tis not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude to ſpeake againſt him, when hee oppoſeth truth; for then many of the Fathers would be very guilty, eſpecially <hi>Iuſtin,</hi> who hath writ a Treatiſe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely againſt him.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe this opinion were falſe, yet 'tis not againſt the faith, and ſo it may ſerve for the better confirmation of that which is true; the ſparkes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, being forc'd out by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, as the ſparkes of fire by the ſtriking of the flint and ſteele. But ſuppoſe too that it were hereticall, and againſt the faith, yet may it be admitted with the ſame priviledge as <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> from whom many more dangerous opinions have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded: as that the world is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:28034:20"/> eternall, that God cannot have while to looke after theſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour things, that after death there is no reward or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſuch like blaſphemies, which ſtrike directly at the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentalls of our Religion.</p>
               <p>So that it is juſtly to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred why ſome ſhould be ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious in theſe daies, as to ſticke cloſer unto him, than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Scripture, as if his Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy were the onely foundation of all divine truthes.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe grounds both S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
                  <hi>Vincentius</hi> and <hi>Senafinus de firmo</hi> (as I have ſeene them quoted) thinke that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was the viol of Gods wrath, which was pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out upon the waters of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by the third Angel; But <note place="margin">Rev. 16. 4.</note> for my part, I thinke the world is much beholden to <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> for all its ſciences. But yet twere a ſhame for theſe later ages to reſt our ſelves meerely upon the labours of our Fore-fathers,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:28034:20"/> as if they had informed us of all things to be knowne, and when wee are ſet upon their ſhoulder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, not to ſee further then they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves did. 'Twere a ſuperſtitious, a lazie opinion to thinke <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> workes the bounds and limits of all humane invention, beyond which there could be no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of reaching. Certainely there are yet many things left to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, and it cannot be any incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience for us, to maintaine a new truth or rectifie an ancient errour.</p>
               <p>But the poſition (ſay ſome) is directly againſt Scripture, for</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Moſes</hi> tels us but of one world, and his Hiſtory of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had beene very imperfect if God had made another.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſpeaking of Gods workes, ſayes he made the world, in the ſingular number, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is but one: '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> and he thinks <note place="margin">Part 1. Q. 47. Art. 3.</note> that none will oppoſe it, but ſuch
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:28034:21"/> who with <hi>Democritus</hi> eſteeme ſome blinde chance, and not any wiſe providence to be the framer of all things.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The opinion of more worlds has in ancient times beene accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a hereſie, and <hi>Baronius</hi> affirmes that for this very reaſon <hi>Virgilius</hi> was caſt out of his Biſhopricke, and excommunicated from the Church. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Annal. Eccl. A. D.</hi> 748.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. A fourth argument there is urged by <hi>Aquinas,</hi> if there bee more worlds than one, then they muſt either be of the ſame or of a diverſe nature, but they are not of the ſame kinde, for this were <note place="margin">ibid.</note> needleſſe and would argue an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>providence, ſince one would have no more perfection than the other; not of divers kinds, for then one of them could not bee called the world or univerſe, ſince it did not containe univerſall perfection, I have cited this argument, becauſe it is ſo much ſtood upon by <hi>Iulius Caeſar la Galla,</hi> one that has pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely <note place="margin">De Phaenom in orbe Lunae</note>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:28034:21"/> writ a Treatiſe againſt this opinion which I now deliver, but the dilemma is ſo blunt that it cannot cut on either ſide, and the conſequences ſo weake that I dare truſt them without an anſwere; And (by the way) you may ſee this author in that place, where he endeavours to prove a neceſſity of one world, doth leave the chiefe matter in hand, and take much needleſſe paines to diſpute againſt <hi>Democritus,</hi> who thought that the world was made by the caſuall concourſe of <hi>atoms</hi> in a great <hi>vacuum.</hi> It ſhould ſeeme that either his cauſe or his skill was weake, or elſe he would have ventured upon a ſtronger adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary. Theſe arguments which I have ſet downe are the chiefeſt which I have met with againſt this ſubject, and yet the beſt of theſe hath not force enough to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger the truth that I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.</p>
               <p>Unto the two firſt it may bee
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:28034:22"/> anſwered, that the negative au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Scripture is not preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in thoſe things which are not the fundamentals of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
               <p>But you'le reply, though it doe not neceſſarily conclude, yet 'tis probable if there had beene another world, wee ſhould have had ſome notice of it in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, 'tis as probable that the Scripture ſhould have infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med us of the planets, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very remarkeable parts of the Creation, and yet neither <hi>Moſes</hi> nor <hi>Iob,</hi> nor the Pſalmes (the places moſt frequent in Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micall obſervations) mention any of them but the Sunne and Moon, and moreover you muſt know that 'tis beſides the ſcope of the Holy Ghoſt either in the new Teſtament or in the old, to reveale any thing unto us concerning the ſecrets of Philoſophy; 'tis not his intent in the new Teſtament, ſince
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:28034:22"/> we cannot conceive how it might any way belong either to the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoricall exegeticall or propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call parts of it: nor is it his intent in the old Teſtament, as is well obſerved by our Countrey-man Maſter WRIGHT. <hi>Non Moſis</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad Gilbert.</note> 
                  <hi>aut Prophetarum inſtitutum fuiſſe videtur Mathematicas aliquas aut Phyſicas ſubtilitates promulgare, ſed ad vulgi captum &amp; loquendi morem quemadmodum nutrices infantulis ſolent ſeſe accommodare.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">'Tis not the endeavour of <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Prophets to diſcover any Mathematicall or Philoſophicall ſubtilties, but rather to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date themſelves to vulgar capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, and ordinary ſpeech, as nurſes are wont to uſe their infants.</q> True indeed, <hi>Moſes</hi> is there to handle the hiſtory of the Creation, but 'tis obſerved that he does not any where meddle with ſuch matters as were very hard to be apprehended, for being to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the common people as well
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:28034:23"/> as others, he does it after a vulgar way, as it is commonly noted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the originall chiefely of thoſe things which were obvious to the ſenſe, and being ſilent of other things which then could not well be apprehended. And therefore <hi>Aquinas</hi> obſerves that <note place="margin">Part 1. Q. 68, Art. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> writes nothing of the aire, becauſe that being inviſible the people knew not whether there were any ſuch body or no. And for this very reaſon, Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> alſo thinkes that there is nothing expreſt concerning the creation of Angels which notwithſtanding are as remarkeable parts of the creatures, and as fit to be knowne as another world. And therefore the Holy Ghoſt too uſes ſuch vulgar expreſſions which ſet things forth rather as they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, then as they are, as when he cals the Moone one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">Gen. 1. 16.</note> lights <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> whereas 'tis the leſt, but one that we can ſee in the whole heavens.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:28034:23"/> So afterwards ſpeaking of the <note place="margin">Gen. 11.</note> great raine which drowned the world, he ſayes, the windowes of heaven were opened, becauſe it ſeemed to come with that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, as if it were poured out from windows in the Firmament. <note place="margin">Sr. <hi>W. Rawly c.</hi> 7. §. 6.</note> So that the phraſes which the Holy Ghoſt uſes concerning theſe things are not to bee underſtood in a literall ſenſe; but rather as vulgar expreſſions, and this rule is ſet downe by Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> where <note place="margin">l. 2. in Gen. Pſal 136. 6</note> ſpeaking concerning that in the Pſalme, <hi>who ſtretched the earth upon the waters,</hi> hee notes that when the words of Scripture ſhall ſeeme to contradict common ſenſe or experience, there are they to be underſtood in a qualified ſence, and not according to the letter. And 'tis obſerved that for want of this rule ſome of the ancients have faſtned ſtrange abſurdities upon the words of the Scripture. So Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> eſteemed it a hereſie to thinke that the Sunne
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:28034:24"/> and Starres were not very hot, as <note place="margin">Wiſd. 2. 4. 17. 5. Ecclus. 43. 3. 4.</note> being againſt the words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 19. 6. where the Pſalmiſt ſayes that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is hid from the heate of the Sunne. So others there are that would prove the heavens not to bee round, out of that place, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104. 2. <hi>He ſtretched out the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Com. in c.</hi> 1. <hi>Gen.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>heavens like a curtaine.</hi> So <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copius</hi> alſo was of opinion that the earth was founded upon the waters, nay hee made it part of his faith, proving it out of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. 2. <hi>Hee hath founded the earth upon the ſeas, and eſtabliſhed it upon the floods.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like abſurdities have followed, when men looke for the grounds of Philoſophy in the words of Scripture. So that, from what hath beene ſaid, I may conclude that the filence of Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning any other world is not ſufficient argument to prove that there is none. Thus for the two firſt arguments.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:28034:24"/>
               <p> Vnto the third, I may anſwer, that this very example is quoted by others, to ſhew the ignorance of thoſe primitive times, who did ſometimes condemne what they did not underſtand, and have often cenſur'd the lawfull &amp; undoubted parts of Mathematiques for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, becauſe they themſelves could not perceive a reaſon of, it and therefore their practiſe in this particular, is no ſufficient teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny againſt us.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, I anſwer to all the above named objections, that the terme World, may be taken in a double ſenſe, more generally for the whole Univerſe, as it implies in it the elementary and aethereall bodies, the ſtarres and the earth. Secondly, more particularly for an inferiour World conſiſting of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Now the maine drift of all theſe arguments, is to confute a plurality of worlds in the firſt ſenſe, and if there were any ſuch, it might, perhaps, ſeeme ſtrange,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:28034:25"/> that <hi>Moſes,</hi> or S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſhould either not know, or not mention its creation. And <hi>Virgilius</hi> was condemned for this opinion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he held <hi>quòd ſit alius mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ſub terrâ, aliuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Sol &amp; Luna,</hi> (as <hi>Baronius)</hi> that within our globe of earth, there was another world, another Sunne and Moone, and ſo he might ſeeme to exclude this from the number of the other creatures.</p>
               <p>But now there is no ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in this opinion, which is here delivered, ſince this world is ſaid to be in the Moone, whoſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is particularly expreſt.</p>
               <p>So that in the firſt ſenſe I yeeld, that there is but one world, which is all that the arguments do prove, but underſtand it in the ſecond ſenſe, and ſo I affirme there may be more, nor doe any of the above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med objections prove the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary.</p>
               <p>Neither can this opinion dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from the divine Wiſdome (as <hi>Aquinas</hi> thinkes) but rather ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:28034:25"/> it, ſhewing a <hi>compendium</hi> of providence, that could make the ſame body a world, and a Moone; a world for habitation, and a Moone for the uſe of others, and the ornament of the whole frame of Nature. For as the members of the body ſerve not onely for the preſervation of themſelves, but for the uſe and conveniency of the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cuſanus de doct. ignor. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> whole, as the hand protects the head as well as ſaves it ſelfe, ſo is it in the parts of the Univerſe, where each one may ſerve as well for the conſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation of that which is within it, as the helpe of others without it.</p>
               <p>I have now in ſome meaſure, ſhewed that a plurality of worlds does not contradict any principle of reaſon or place of Scripture, and ſo cleared the firſt part of that ſuppoſition which is implied in the opinion.</p>
               <p>It may next be enquired, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 'tis poſſible there may be a globe of elements in that which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:28034:26"/> we call the aethereall parts of the Univerſe; for if this (as it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common opinion) be priviledged from any change or corruption, it will be in vaine then to imagine any element there, and if we will have another world, we muſt then ſeeke out ſome other place for its ſituation. The third Propoſition therefore ſhall be this.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>Propoſition. 3. <hi>That the heavens doe not conſiſt of any ſuch pure matter which can priviledge them from the like change and corruption, as theſe inferiour bodies are liable unto.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT hath beene often queſtioned amongſt the ancient Fathers and Philoſophers, what kind of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſhould be ſo, which the heavens are framed, whether or no of any fifth ſubſtance diſtinct from the foure elements, as <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:28034:26"/> holds, and with him ſome of <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De coelo. li.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</note> the late Schoolemen, whoſe ſubtill braines could not be content to attribute to thoſe vaſt glorious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but common materialls, and therefore they themſelves had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take paines to preferre them to ſome extraordinary nature, whereas notwithſtanding, all the arguments they could invent, were not able to convince a neceſſity of any ſuch matter, as is confeſt by their owne <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Colleg. Connimb. de coelo. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 6. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</note> ſide. It were much to be deſired, that theſe men had not in other caſes, as well as this, multiplied things without neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and as if there had not beene enough to be knowne in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of nature, have ſpun out new ſubjects from their owne braines to finde more worke for future ages, I ſhall not mention their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, ſince 'tis already confeſt, that they are none of them of any neceſſary conſequence, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, you may ſee them ſet downe in any of the bookes, <hi>de Coelo.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:28034:27"/>
               <p> But it is the generall conſent of the Fathers, and the opinion of <hi>Lombard,</hi> that the heavens conſiſt of the ſame matter with theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary bodies. Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Hexam. lib.</hi> 4.</note> confident of it, that hee eſteemes the contrary a hereſie. True in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, they differ much among themſelves, ſome thinking them to be made of fire, others of water, but herein they generally agree, that they are all framed of ſome element or other. For a better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of this, you may ſee <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovicus Molina, Euſeb. Nirem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergius,</hi> with divers others. The <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In opere</hi> 6. <hi>dierum. diſput.</hi> 5.</note> venerable <hi>Bede</hi> thought the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets to conſiſt of all the foure ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and 'tis likely that the other parts are of an aereous ſubſtance, <note place="margin">In lib. de Mundi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit.</note> as will be ſhewed afterward; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I cannot now ſtand to recite the arguments for either, I have onely urged theſe Authorities to countervaile <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and the Schoolmen, and the better to make way for a proofe of their corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:28034:27"/>
               <p> The next thing then to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired after, is, whether they be of a corruptible nature, not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. 12.</note> they can be deſtroyed by God, for this Scripture puts out of doubt.</p>
               <p>Nor whether or no in a long time they would weare away and grow worſe, for from any ſuch feare they have beene lately privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. But whether they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of ſuch changes and viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, <note place="margin">By Doctor <hi>Hackwel Apol.</hi>
                  </note> as this inferiour world is liable unto.</p>
               <p>The two chiefe opinions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this, have both erred in ſome extremity, the one ſide go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo farre from the other, that they have both gone beyond the right, whileſt <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> hath op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the truth, as well as the Stoicks.</p>
               <p>Some of the Ancients have thought, that the heavenly bodies have ſtood in need of nouriſhment from the elements, by which they were continually ſeed, and ſo had
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:28034:28"/> divers alterations by reaſon of their food, this is fathered on <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclitus,</hi> followed by that great <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plutarch. de plac. philoſ. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Nat. Hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> Naturaliſt <hi>Pliny,</hi> and in generall attributed to all the Stoicks. You may ſee <hi>Seneca</hi> expreſſely to this purpoſe in theſe words, <hi>Ex illa ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta omnibus animalibus, omnibus ſatis, omnibus ſtellis dividuntur, hinc</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. Quaeſt. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>profertur quo ſuſtincantur tot Sydera tam exercitata, tam avida, per diem, noctem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, ut in opere, ita in paſtu.</hi> Speaking of the earth, he ſaies, from thence it is, that nouriſhment is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided to al the living creatures, the Plants and the Starres, hence were ſuſtained ſo many conſtellations, ſo laborious, ſo greedy both day and night, as well in their feeding as working. Thus alſo <hi>Lucan</hi> ſings, <hi>Necnon Oceano paſci Phoebum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <q>polum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> credimus.</q>
               <p>Unto theſe <hi>Ptolome</hi> alſo that lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Egyptian ſeemed to agree, <note place="margin">10. <hi>Apoſtel.</hi>
                  </note> when he affirmes that the body of the Moone is moiſter, and cooler than any of the other Planets, by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:28034:28"/> reaſon of the earthly vapours that are exhaled unto it. You ſee theſe ancients thought the Heavens to be ſo farre from this imagined in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibility, that rather like the weakeſt bodies they ſtood in need of ſome continuall nouriſhment without which they could not ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and his followers <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De coelo. li.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> were ſo farre from this, that they thought thoſe glorious bodies could not containe within them any ſuch principles, as might make them lyable to the leaſt change or corruption, and their chiefe reaſon was, becauſe we could not in ſo long a ſpace diſcerne any alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration amongſt them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but unto this I anſwere.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Suppoſing we could not, yet would it not hence follow that there were none, as hee himſelfe in effect doth confeſſe in another place; for ſpeaking concerning our knowledge of the Heavens, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Coelo. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</note> he ſayes 'tis very imperfect and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:28034:29"/> difficult, by reaſon of the vaſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thoſe bodies from us, and becauſe the changes which may happen unto it, are not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bigge enough or frequent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to fall within the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and obſervation of our ſenſes; no wonder then if hee himſelfe bee deceived in his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions concerning theſe parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though wee could not by our ſenſes ſee ſuch alterations, yet our reaſon might perhaps ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently convince us of them. Nor can wee well conceive how the Sunne ſhould reflect againſt the Moone, and yet not produce ſome alteration of heate. <hi>Diogenes</hi> the Philoſopher w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hence perſwaded that thoſe ſcorching heates had burnt the Moone into the forme of a Pumice-ſtone.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I anſwere that there have beene ſome alterations obſerved there; witneſſe thoſe comets which have been ſeene above the Moon.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:28034:29"/> So that though <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence were ſufficient, when he proved that the heavens were not corruptible, becauſe there have not any changes beene obſerved in it, yet this by the ſame reaſon muſt bee as prevalent, that the Heavens are corruptible, becauſe there have beene ſo many altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions obſerved there; but of theſe together with a farther confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this propoſition, I ſhall have occaſion to ſpeake after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards; In the meane ſpace, I will referre the Reader to that worke of <hi>Scheiner</hi> a late Jeſuite which he titles his <hi>Roſa Vrſina,</hi> where hee may ſee this point concerning the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>par.</hi> 2. <hi>cy.</hi> 24, 35.</note> corruptibility of the Heavens largely handled and ſufficiently confirmed.</p>
               <p>There are ſome other things, on which I might here take an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to enlarge my ſelfe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are directly handled by many others, and doe not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately belong to the chiefe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:28034:30"/> matter in hand, I ſhall therefore referre the Reader to their authors, and omit any large proofe of them my ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe, as deſiring all poſſible brevity.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt is this: That there are no ſolid Orbes. If there be a habitable world in the Moone (which I now affirme) it muſt follow, that her Orbe is not ſolid as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſuppoſed; and if not her, why any of the other. I rather thinke that they are all of a fluid (perhaps aereous) ſubſtance. Saint <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour <note place="margin">Iſa. 51. 6.</note> to prove this out of that place in <hi>Iſay,</hi> where they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ant. lect. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> to ſmoake, as they are both quoted by <hi>Rhodiginus, Euſebius, Nicrembergius</hi> doth likewiſe from that place confute the ſolidity and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hist. nat. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11. 13</note> incorruptibility of the Heavens, and cites for the ſame interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the authority of <hi>Euſtachius</hi> of <hi>Antioch;</hi> and Saint <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I am ſure ſeemes to aſſent unto <note place="margin">In lib. ſup. Gen. ad lit.</note> this opinion, though he does often
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:28034:30"/> in his other workes contradict it. The teſtimony of other Fathers to this purpoſe you may ſee in <hi>Sixtus Senenſis. l.</hi> 5. <hi>Biblioth. annot.</hi> 14. but for your better ſatisfaction herein, I ſhall referre you to the above named <hi>Scheiner</hi> in his <hi>Roſa</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 11. 2 <hi>cap.</hi> 7. 26, 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Vrſina,</hi> in whom you may ſee both authorities and reaſon, and very largely and diſtinctly ſet downe for this opinion, for the better confirmation of which he adjoynes alſo ſome authenticall Epiſtles of <hi>Fredericus Caeſius Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus</hi> a Noble Prince written to <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> containing divers rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the ſame purpoſe, you may alſo ſee the ſame truth ſet downe by <hi>Iohannes Pena</hi> in his preface to <hi>Euclids Opticks,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtoph. Rothmannus,</hi> both who thought the Firmament to bee onely aire: and though the noble <hi>Tycho</hi> doe <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſtella.</hi> 15 72. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> diſpute againſt them, yet he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe holds, <hi>Quod propius ad veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis penetralia accedit haec opinio, quam Ariſtotelica vulgariter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probata,</hi>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:28034:31"/> 
                  <hi>quae coelum pluribus realibus atque imperviis orbibus cipra rem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plevit.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That this opinion comes neerer to the truth than that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon one of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> which hath to no purpoſe filled the Heavens with ſuch reall and impervious Orbes.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. There is no element of fire, which muſt bee held with this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion here delivered; for if wee ſuppoſe a world in the Moone, then it will follow, that the ſpheare of fire, either is not there where 'tis uſually placed in the concavity of his Orbe, or elſe that there is no ſuch thing at all, which is moſt probable ſince there are not any ſuch ſolid Orbes, that by their ſwift motion might heate and enkindle the adjoyning aire, which is imagined to bee the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of that element. Concerning this ſee <hi>Cardan, Iohannes Pena</hi> that learned Frenchman, the noble <hi>Tycho,</hi> with divers others who have purpoſely handled this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:28034:31"/> 3. I might adde a third, <hi>viz.</hi> that there is no Muſicke of the ſpheares, for if they be not ſolid, how can their motion cauſe any ſuch ſound as is conceived? I doe the rather medle with this, becauſe <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeakes as if a man might very conveniently heare that har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, if he were an inhabitant in the Moone. But I gueſſe that hee ſaid this out of incogitancy, and did not well conſider thoſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary conſequences which depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon his opinion. However the world would have no great loſſe in being deprived of this Muſicke, unleſſe at ſometimes we had the priviledge to heare it: Then indeed <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew thinks <note place="margin">De ſomniis.</note> it would ſave us the charges of diet, and we might live at an eaſie rate by feeding at the eare onely, and receiving no other nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and for this very reaſon (ſaies hee) was <hi>Moſes</hi> enabled to tarry forty daies and forty nights in the Mount without eating any
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:28034:32"/> thing, becauſe he there heard the melody of the Heavens, <hi>-Riſum teneatis.</hi> I know this Muſicke hath had great patrons both ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and prophane authors, ſuch as <hi>Ambroſe, Bede, Boetius, Anſelme, Plato, Cicero</hi> and others, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not now, I thinke affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by any, I ſhall not therefore beſtow either paines or time in arguing againſt it.</p>
               <p>It may ſuffice that I have onely named theſe three laſt, and for the two more neceſſary, have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Reader to others for ſatisfaction. I ſhall in the next place proceed to the nature of the Moones body, to know whether that be capable of any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as may make it poſſible to be inhabited, and what thoſe qualities are wherein it more neerely agrees with our earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proposition">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:28034:32"/>
               <head>Propoſition 4. <hi>That the Moone is a ſolid, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, opacous body.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall not neede to ſtand long in the proofe of this propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſince it is a truth already agreed on by the generall conſent of the moſt and the beſt Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is ſolid in oppoſition to fluid, as is the ayer, for how o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe could it beate backe the light which it receives from the Sunne?</p>
               <p>But here it may be queſtioned, whether or no the Moone beſtow her light upon us by the reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sunne-beames from the ſuperficies of her body, or elſe by her owne illumination. Some there are who affirme this latter part. So <hi>Averroes, Caelius Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diginus, Iulius Caeſar, &amp;c.</hi> and their
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:28034:33"/> reaſon is becauſe this light is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in many places, whereas <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Coelo l.</hi> 2. <hi>com.</hi> 49. <hi>Ant. lection. l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>de phaenom. lunae. c.</hi> 11.</note> thoſe bodies which give light by reflexion can there onely be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived where the angle of reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is equall to the angle of inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and this is onely in one place, as in a looking-glaſſe thoſe beames which are reflected from it cannot bee perceived in every place where you may ſee the glaſſe, but onely there where your eye is placed on the ſame line whereon the beames are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected.</p>
               <p>But to this I anſwere, that the argument will not hold of ſuch bodies, whoſe ſuperficies is full of unequall parts and gibboſities as the Moone is. Wherefore it is as well the more probable as the more common opinion, that her light proceedes from both theſe cauſes, from reflexion and illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; nor doth it herein differ from our earth ſince that alſo hath ſome light by illumination: for
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:28034:33"/> how otherwiſe would the parts about us in a Sunne-ſhine day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſo bright, when as all the rayes of reflexion cannot enter into our eye?</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is compact, and not a ſpun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut. de pla. phil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>Opt. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Com. Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bac. Theo. p.</hi> 164.</note> and porous ſubſtance. But this is denied by <hi>Diogenes, Vitellio,</hi> and <hi>Reinoldus,</hi> and ſome others, who held the Moone to be of the ſame kind of nature as a Pumice ſtone, and this, ſay they, is the reaſon why in the Sunnes eclipſes there appeares within her a duskiſh rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy colour, becauſe the Sun beames being refracted in paſſing through the pores of her body, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be repreſented under ſuch a colour.</p>
               <p>But I reply, if this be the cauſe of her redneſſe, then why doth ſhe not appeare under the ſame forme when ſhee is about a ſextile aſpect, and the darkned part of her body is diſcernable? for then alſo doe the ſame rayes paſſe through her, and therefore in all likelihood
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:28034:34"/> ſhould produce the ſame effect, and notwithſtanding thoſe beames are then diverted from us, that they cannot enter into our eyes by a ſtreight line, yet muſt the colour ſtill remaine viſible in her body, and beſides according to this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the ſpots would not alwaies be the ſame, but divers as the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſtance of the Sunne requires. Againe, if the Sunne beames did <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scaliger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit.</hi> 80. § 13.</note> paſſe through her, why then hath ſhe not a taile as the Comets? why doth ſhe appeare in ſuch an exact round? and not rather attended with a long flame, ſicne it is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this penetration of the Sunne beames that is uſually attributed to be the cauſe of beards in blazing ſtarres.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is opacous, not tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent or diaphanous like Chryſtall or glaſſe, as <hi>Empedocles</hi> thought, <note place="margin">Plut. de facie lunae.</note> who held the Moone to be a globe of pure congealed aire, like haile incloſed in a ſpheare of fire, for then,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:28034:34"/> 1. Why does ſhee not alwaies appeare in the full? ſince the light is diſperſed through all her body?</p>
               <p n="2">2. How can the interpoſition of her body ſo darken the Sunne, or cauſe ſuch great eclipſes as have <note place="margin">Thucid. Livii. Plut. de facie Lunae.</note> turned day into night, that have diſcovered the ſtars, and frighted the birds with ſuch a ſudden dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that they fell downe upon the earth, as it is related indivers Hiſtories. And therefore <hi>Herodotus</hi> tellin of an eclipſe which fell in <hi>Xerxes</hi> time, deſcribes it thus: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Herodot. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 37.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Sunne leaving his wonted ſeat in the heavens, vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away: all which argues ſuch a great darkneſſe, as could not have beene, if her body had beene perſpicuous. Yet ſome there are who interpret all theſe relations to be hyperbolicall expreſſions, and the noble <hi>Tich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> thinkes it na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally impoſſible, that any eclipſe ſhould cauſe ſuch darkeneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:28034:35"/> the body of the Moone can never totally cover the Sunne; however, in this he is ſingular, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other Aſtronomers (if I may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve <hi>Keplar)</hi> being on the contrary opinion, by reaſon the Diameter of the Moone does for the moſt part appeare bigger to us then the Diameter of the Sunne.</p>
               <p>But here <hi>Julius Caeſar</hi> once more, puts in to hinder our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De phaenom. Lunae. c.</hi> 11.</note> The Moone (ſaith he) is not altogether opacous, becauſe 'tis ſtill of the ſame nature with the heavens, which are incapable of totall opacity: and his reaſon is, becauſe perſpicuity is an inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable accident of thoſe purer bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and this hee thinkes muſt neceſſarily be granted, for he ſtops there, and proves no further; but to this I ſhall deferre an anſwer, till hee hath made up his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>We may frequently ſee, that her body does ſo eclipſe the Sunne, as our earth doth the Moone; ſince
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:28034:35"/> then the like interpoſition of them both, doth produce the like ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, they muſt neceſſarily be of the like natures, that is alike opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous, which is the thing to be ſhewed; and this was the reaſon (as the Interpreters gueſſe) why <note place="margin">In lib. de animalib.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> affirmed the Moone to be of the earths nature, becauſe of their agreement in opacity, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all the other elements ſave that, are in ſome meaſure perſpicuous.</p>
               <p>But the greateſt difference which may ſeeme to make our earth altogether unlike the Moon, is, becauſe the one is a bright bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and hath light of its owne, and the other a groſſe darke body which cannot ſhine at all. 'Tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite therefore, that in the next place I cleare this doubt, and ſhew that the Moone hath no more light of her owne than our earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proposition">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:28034:36"/>
               <head>Propoſition. 5. <hi>That the Moone hath not any light of her owne.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Twas the fancy of ſome of the Jewes, and more eſpecially of <hi>Rabbi Simeon,</hi> that the Moone <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Toſtatus in</hi> 1. <hi>Gen. Hieron. de</hi> 5. <hi>Hide. Haebreoma. l</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> was nothing elſe but a contracted Sunne, and that both thoſe planets at their firſt creation were equall both in light and quantity, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God did then call them both great lights, therefore they infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that they muſt be both equall in bigneſſe. But a while after (as the tradition goes) the ambitious Moone put up her complaint to God againſt the Sun, ſhewing, that it was not fit there ſhould be two ſuch great lights in the heavens, a Monarchie would beſt become the place of order and harmony. Upon this, God commanded her to contract her ſelfe into a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower compaſſe, but ſhee being
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:28034:36"/> much diſcontented hereat, replies, What! becauſe I have ſpoken that which is reaſon and equity, muſt I therefore be diminiſhed? This ſentence could not chuſe but much trouble her; and for this reaſon was ſhee in much diſtreſſe and griefe for a long ſpace, but that her ſorrow might be ſome way paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, God bid her be of good cheere, becauſe her priviledges and charter ſhould be greater then the Suns, he ſhould appeare in the day time onely, ſhee both in the day and night, but her melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly being not ſatisfied with this, ſhe replied againe, that that alas was no benefit, for in the day time ſhe ſhould be either not ſeene, or not noted. Wherefore, God to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her up, promiſed, that his people the Iſraelites ſhould cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate all their feaſt and holy daies by a computation of her moneths, but this being not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent her, ſhee has looked very melancholy ever ſince; howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:28034:37"/> ſhee hath ſtill reſerved much light of her owne.</p>
               <p>Others there were, that did thinke the Moone to be around globe, the one halfe of whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was of a bright ſubſtance, the other halfe being darke, and the divers converſions of thoſe ſides towards our eyes, cauſed the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of her appearances: of this opinion was <hi>Beroſus,</hi> as he is cited <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 9. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecturae in enarrat. Pſal morum.</hi>
                  </note> by <hi>Vitruvius,</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin</hi> thought it was probable enough, but this fancy is almoſt equally ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd with the former, and both of them ſound rather like fables, then philoſophicall truths. You may commonly ſee how this latter does contradict frequent and eaſie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, for 'tis obſerved, that that ſpot which is perceived about her middle, when ſhee is in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, may be diſcern'd in the ſame place when ſhe is in the ful: whence it muſt follow, that the ſame part which was before darkned, is after inlightened, and that the one part
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:28034:37"/> is not alwaies darke and the other light of it ſelfe, but enough of this, I would be loth to make an enemy, that I may afterwards overcome him, or beſtow time in proving that, which is already granted, I ſuppoſe now, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them hath any patrons, and therfore need no confutation.</p>
               <p>Tis agreed upon by all ſides, that this Planet receives moſt of her light from the Sunne, but the chiefe controverſie is, whether or no ſhe hath any of her owne? The greater multitude affirme this. <hi>Cardan</hi> amongſt the reſt, is very confident of it, and he thinks that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Subtil. lib.</hi> 3.</note> if any of us were in the Moone at the time of her greateſt eclipſe, <hi>Lunam aſpiceremus non ſecus ac in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeris cereis ſplendidiſſimis ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in eas oculis defixis caecutiremus;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">wee ſhould per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſo great a brightneſſe of her owne, that would blind us with the meere ſight, and when ſhee is enlightened by the Sunne,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:28034:38"/> then no eagles eye if there were any there, is able to looke upon her.</q> This <hi>Cardan</hi> ſaies, and hee doth but ſay it without bringing any proofe for its confirmation. However I will ſet downe the arguments that are uſually urged for this opinion, and they are ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken either from Scripture or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; from Scripture is urged that place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. where it is ſaid, <hi>There is one glory of the Sunne, and an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther glory of the Moone. Vlyſſes Albergettus</hi> urges that in <hi>Math.</hi> 24. 29. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Moone ſhall not give her light:</hi> therefore (ſayes he) ſhe hath ſome of her owne.</p>
               <p>But to theſe we may eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that the glory and light there ſpoken off, may be ſaid to bee hers though it bee derived, as you may ſee in many other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
               <p>The arguments from reaſon are taken either</p>
               <p n="1">1. From that light which is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:28034:38"/> diſcerned in her, when there is a totall eclipſe of her owne body, or of the Sunne.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the light which is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the darker part of her body, when ſhe is but a little diſtant from the Sunne.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For when there are any totall eclipſes, there appeares in her body a great redneſſe, and many times light enough to cauſe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable ſhade, as common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doth ſufficiently mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt: but this cannot come from the Sunne, ſince at ſuch times either the earth or her owne body ſhades her from the Sunne-beames, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it muſt proceede from her owne light.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Two or three daies after the new Moone, wee may perceive light in her whole body, whereas the rayes of the Sun reflect but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a ſmall part of that which is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, therefore 'tis likely that there is ſome light of her owne.</p>
               <p>In anſwering to theſe objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:28034:39"/> I ſhall firſt ſhew, that this light cannot be her owne, and then declare that which is the true rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it.</p>
               <p>That it is not her owne, appeares</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the variety of it at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times; for 'tis commonly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved that ſometimes 'tis of a brighter, ſometimes of a darker appearance, now redder and at another time of a more duskiſh colour. The obſervation of this variety in divers eclipſes, you may ſee ſet downe by <hi>Keplar</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Opt. Aſtron. c.</hi> 7. <hi>num.</hi> 3.</note> many others, but now this could not be if that light were her owne, that being conſtantly the ſame, and without any reaſon of ſuch an alteration: So that thus I may argue.</p>
               <p>If there were any light proper to the Moone, then would that Planet appeare brighteſt when ſhe is eclipſed in her Perige being neereſt to the earth, and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently more obſcure and duskiſh when ſhe is in her Apoge or far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:28034:39"/> from it; the reaſon is, becauſe the neerer any enlightned body comes to the ſight, by ſo much the more ſtrong are the ſpecies and the better perceived. This ſequell is granted by ſome of our adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and they are the very words <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De nova ſtella. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> of noble <hi>Tycho, Si luna genuino gauderet lumine, uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cum in um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra terrae eſſet, illud non amitteret, ſed eo evidentius exereret, omne enim lumen in tenebris, plus ſplendet cum alio majore fulgore non praepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur.</hi> If the Moone had any light of her owne, then would ſhe not loſe it in the earth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhadow, but rather ſhine more clearely, ſince every light appeares greater in the darke, when it is not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by a more perſpicuous brightneſſe.</p>
               <p>But now the event fals out cleane contrary, (as obſervation <note place="margin">Reinhold <hi>comment. in Purb. Theor. pag.</hi> 164.</note> doth manifeſt, and our oppoſites themſelves doe grant) the Moone appearing with a more reddiſh and cleare light when ſhe is eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:28034:40"/> being in her Apoge or fartheſt diſtance, and a more blackiſh yron colour when ſhee is in her Perige or neareſt to us, therefore ſhee hath not any light of her owne. Nor may we thinke that the earths ſhadow can cloud the proper light of the Moone from appearing, or take away any thing from her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent brightneſſe, for this were to thinke a ſhadow to be a body, an opinion altogether miſ-becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a Philoſopher, as <hi>Tycho</hi> grants in the fore-cited place; <hi>Nec umbra terrae corporeum quid eſt, out de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſa aliqua ſubſtanti, aut lunae lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men obtenebrare poſſit, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> id viſui noſtro praeripere, ſed eſt quaedam privatio luminis ſolaris, ob interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum opacum corpus terrae.</hi> Nor is the earths ſhadow any corporall thing, or thicke ſubſtance, that it can cloud the Moones bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or take it away from our ſight, but it is a meere privation of the Sunnes light by reaſon of the interpoſition of the earths o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacous body.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:28034:40"/> 2. If ſhe had any light of her owne then that would in it ſelfe be, either ſuch a ruddy brightneſſe as appeares in the eclipſes, or elſe ſuch a leaden duskiſh light as wee ſee in the darker parts of her body, when ſhe is a little paſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction. (That it muſt be one of theſe may follow from the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite arguments) but it is neither of theſe, therefore ſhe hath none of her owne.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis not ſuch a ruddy light as appeares in eclipſes, for then why can we not ſee the like red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, when we may diſcerne the obſcurer parts of the Moone?</p>
               <p>You will ſay, perhaps, that then the neereneſſe of that grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light takes away that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>I reply, this cannot be, for then why does Mars ſhine with his wonted redneſſe, when he is neere the Moone? or why cannot her greater brightneſſe make him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare white as the other Planets?
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:28034:41"/> nor can there be any reaſon given why that greater light ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent her body under a falſe colour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis not ſuch a duskiſh lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den light, as we ſee in the darker part of her body, when ſhee is about a ſextile Aſpect diſtant from the Sunne, for then why does ſhe appeare red in the eclipſes, ſince the more ſhade cannot chooſe ſuch variety, for 'tis the nature of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by its oppoſition, rather to make things appeare of a more white and cleare brightneſſe than they are in themſelves, or if it be the ſhade, yet thoſe parts of the Moone are then in the ſhade of her body, and therefore in reaſon ſhould have the like redneſſe. Since then neither of theſe lights are hers, it followes that ſhe hath none of her owne. Nor is this a ſingular opinion, but it hath had many learned patrons, ſuch was <hi>Macrobius,</hi> who being for this quoted of <hi>Rhodiginus,</hi> he cals him <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Somn. Scip. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20.</note>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:28034:41"/> 
                  <hi>vir re conditiſſimae ſcientiae,</hi> a man <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lect. antiq. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> who knew more then ordinary Philoſophers, thus commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the opinion in the credit of the Authour. To him aſſents the Venerable <hi>Bede,</hi> upon whom the gloſſe hath this compariſon. As <note place="margin">In lib. de natur. rerum</note> the Looking-glaſſe repreſents not any image within it ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it receive ſome from without; ſo the Moone hath not any light, but what is beſtowed by the Sun. To theſe agreed <hi>Albertus Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Scaliger, Maeſlin,</hi> and more <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Coae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis. Q.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>Art.</hi> 21. <hi>Exercit.</hi> 62. 1. <hi>Epitom. Aſtron. l.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 2.</note> eſpecially <hi>Mulapertius,</hi> whoſe words are more pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe then others, and therefore I ſhall ſet them downe as you may finde them in his preface to his Treatiſe concerning the <hi>Auſtriaca ſydera; Luna, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus, &amp; Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, terreſtris &amp; humidae ſunt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae, ideo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> de ſuo non lucere, ſicut nec terra.</hi> The Moone, <hi>Venus,</hi> and <hi>Mercurie</hi> (ſaith he) are of an earthly and moyſt ſubſtance, and therefore have no more light of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:28034:42"/> their owne, then the earth hath. Nay ſome there are who thinke that all the other Starres doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that light, whereby they appeare viſible to us from the Sunne, ſo <hi>Ptolomie, Iſidere Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenſis,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Originum l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 60. <hi>De Coelo: l.</hi> 2. <hi>De ratione tempor. c.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Albertus Magnus,</hi> and <hi>Bede,</hi> much more then muſt the Moone ſhine with a borrowed light.</p>
               <p>But enough of this. I have now ſufficiently ſhewed what at the firſt I promiſed, that this light is not proper to the Moone. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines in the next place, that I tell you the true reaſon of it. And here, I thinke 'tis probable that the light which appeares in the Moone at the eclipſes is nothing elſe but the ſecond ſpecies of the Sunnes rayes which paſſe through the ſhadow unto her body: and from a mixture of this ſecond light with the ſhadow, ariſes that redneſſe which at ſuch times ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares unto us. I may call it <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men crepuſculum,</hi> the <hi>Aurora</hi> of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:28034:42"/> the Moone, or ſuch a kinde of bluſhing light, that the Sunne cauſes when he is neere his riſing, when he beſtowes ſome ſmall light upon the thicker vapours. Thus wee ſee commonly the Sunne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Horizon, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion growing weake, how his beames make the waters appeare very red.</p>
               <p>The Moabites in <hi>Iehorams</hi> time when they roſe early in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <note place="margin">2 King. 3. 22.</note> and beheld the waters a farre off, miſtooke them for blood. <hi>Et cauſa hujus eſt quia radius ſolaris in Aurora contrahit quandam rube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, propter vapores combuſtos manentes circa ſuperficiem terrae, per quos radii tranſeunt, &amp; ideo cum repercutiantur in aqua ad oculos noſtros, trahunt ſecum eundem ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borem, &amp; faciunt apparere locum aquarum, in quo eſt repercuſſia eſſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>Quaeſt. in hoc cap.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>rubrum</hi> ſaith <hi>Toſtatus.</hi> The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe of his rayes, which being in the lower vapours, thoſe doe convey an imperfect mixed
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:28034:43"/> light upon the waters. Thus the Moon being in the earths ſhadow, and the Sunne beames which are round about it, not being able to come directly unto her body, yet ſome ſecond raies there are, which paſſing through the ſhadow, make her appeare in that ruddy colour: So that ſhe muſt appeare brighteſt, when ſhee is eclipſed, being in her Apoge or greateſt diſtance from us, becauſe then the cone of the earths ſhadow is leſſe, and the refraction is made through a nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower medium. So on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, ſhe muſt be repreſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a more darke and obſcure forme when ſhe is eclipſed, being in her Perige, or neereſt to the earth, becauſe then ſhe is involved in a greater ſhadow, or bigger part of the cone, and ſo the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraction paſſing through a greater medium, the light muſt needs be weaker which doth proceed from it. If you aske now what the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be of that light which we
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:28034:43"/> diſcorne in the darker part of the new Moone. I anſwer, 'tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected from our earth which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes as great a brightneſſe to that Planet, as it receives from it. This I ſhall have occaſion to prove af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward.</p>
               <p>I have now done with theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions which were ſet downe to cleare the paſſage, and confirme the ſuppoſitions implied in the opinion, I ſhall in the next place proceed to a more direct treating of the chiefe matter in hand.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proposition">
               <head>Propoſition 6. <hi>That there is a world in the Moone, hath beene the direct opinion of many ancient, with ſome moderne Mathematicians, and may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be deduced from the tenents of others.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SInce this opinion may be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of ſingularity, I ſhall
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:28034:44"/> therefore firſt confirme it by ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient authority of divers authours, both ancient and moderne, that ſo I may the better cleare it from the prejudice either of an upſtart fancy, or an obſolete errour. This is by ſome attributed to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus,</hi> one of the moſt ancient, Greeke Poets, who ſpeaking of the Moone, ſaies thus, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut. de plac. phil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13</note> That it hath many mountaines and cities, and houſes in it. To him aſſented <hi>Xenophanes, Anaxagoras, Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ibid. c.</hi> 25.</note> and <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> all who thought it to have firme ſolid ground, like to our earth, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diog. Laert. l.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; l.</hi> 9.</note> in it many large fields, cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion grounds, and divers inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, unto theſe agreed <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> who thought that our earth was but one of the Planets which moved round about the Sunne, (as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Coelo. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> relates it of him) and the <hi>Pythagoreans</hi> in generall did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that the Moone alſo was terreſtriall, that ſhe was inhabited
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:28034:44"/> as this lower world, That thoſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creature, &amp; plants which are in her, exceed any of the like kind with us in the ſame proportion, as their daies are longer than ours: <hi>viz.</hi> by 15. times. This <hi>Pythagoras</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut. ibid. cap.</hi> 30.</note> was eſteemed by all, of a moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wit, as appeares eſpecially by his valuation amongſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> who being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded by the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle to erect a ſtatue to the wiſeſt <hi>Graecian,</hi> the Senate determined <hi>Pythagoras</hi> to be meant, preferring <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. Nat. Hiſt. l</hi> 34. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> him in their judgements before the divine <hi>Socrates,</hi> whom their Gods pronounc'd the wiſeſt. Some think him a <hi>Jew</hi> by birth, but moſt agree that hee was much converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the learneder ſort, and Prieſts of that Nation, by whom he was informed of many ſecrets, and perhaps, this opinion, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he vented afterwards in <hi>Greece,</hi> where he was much oppoſed by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in ſome worded diſputations, but never confuted by any ſolid reaſon.</p>
               <p>To this opinion of <hi>Pythagoras</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:28034:45"/> did <hi>Plato</hi> alſo aſſent, when hee conſidered that there was the like eclipſe made by the earth, and this, that it had no light of its owne, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plat. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viviis. Macreb. Somn. Scip. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> that it was ſo full of ſpots. And therefore wee may often reade in him and his followers, of an <hi>aetherea terra,</hi> and <hi>lunares populi,</hi> an aethereall earth, and inhabiters in the Moone; but afterwards this was mixed with many ridiculous fancies: for ſome of them conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the myſteries implied in the number 3. concluded that there muſt neceſſarily be a Trinity of worlds, whereof the firſt is this of ours, the ſecond in the Moone whoſe element of water is repreſented by the ſpheare of <hi>Mercury,</hi> the aire by <hi>Venus,</hi> and the fire by the Sunne. And that the whole Univerſe might the better end in earth as it began, they have contrived it, that <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall be a ſpheare of the fire, <hi>Iupiter</hi> of aire, <hi>Saturne</hi> of water; and above all theſe, the Elyſian fields, ſpacious
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:28034:45"/> and pleaſant places appointed for the habitation of thoſe unſported ſoules, that either never were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in, or elſe now have freed themſelves from any commerce <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exercit.</hi> 62.</note> with the body. <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſpeaking of this <hi>Platonick</hi> fancie, <hi>quae intres trientes mundum quaſi aſſem divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit,</hi> thinks 'tis confutation enough, to ſay, 'tis <hi>Plato's.</hi> However for the firſt part of this aſſertion, it was aſſented unto by many others, and by reaſon of the groſſeneſſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of this planet, '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>was fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called <hi>quaſi terra coeleſtis,</hi> as being eſteemed the ſediment and more imperfect part of thoſe <note place="margin">De facie Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae.</note> purer bodies, you may ſee this proved by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> in that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull work which he properly made for the confirmation of this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Instit. ad diſcip. Plat. Coel. Rhodig. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> particular. With him agreed <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinous</hi> and <hi>Plotinus,</hi> later Writers. Unto theſe I might alſo adde the imperfect teſtimony of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> whoſe authority of grant can adde but little credit to this opinion,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:28034:46"/> becauſe hee was an ignorant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſter, but yet conſider that ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, from whence hee derived moſt of his knowledge, and then, perhaps, his witneſſe may carry with it ſome probability. Hee is commonly thought by birth to be an Iſmaelite, being inſtructed by the Jewes in the ſecrets of their philoſophy and, perhaps, learned this from thoſe Rabbies, for in <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Azoara.</hi> 57. <hi>&amp;</hi> 65.</note> his <hi>Alcaron,</hi> hee talkes much of mountaines, pleaſant fields, and cleare rivers in the heavens, but becauſe he was for the maine very unlearned, hee was not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver any thing ſo diſtinctly as he was informed. The Cardinall <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cuſa. de dect. ign. l.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.</note> and <hi>Iornandus Brunus,</hi> held a particular world in every Starre, and therefore one of them defining our earth, he ſaies, it is <hi>ſtella quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam nobilis, quae lunam &amp; calorem &amp; influentiam habet aliam, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſam ab omnibus aliis ſtellis;</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">a noble ſtarre having a diſtinct light, heat and influence from all
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:28034:46"/> the reſt.</q> Unto this <hi>Nichol. Hill,</hi> a country man of ours was inclined, when hee ſaid <hi>Aſtrea terrae natura</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Philoſ. epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur. part.</hi> 434.</note> 
                  <hi>probabilis eſt:</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">That 'tis probable the earth hath a ſtarry nature.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But the opinion which I have here delivered was more directly proved by <hi>Maſlin Keplar,</hi> and <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> each of them late wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and famous men for their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <note place="margin">In Theſibus diſſertatio cum Nic. Hill. Nunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Sydereus.</note> skill in Aſtronomy. As for thoſe workes of <hi>Maeſlin</hi> and <hi>Kep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> wherein they doe more expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treate of this opinion, I have not yet had the happineſſe to ſee them. However their opinions appeare plaine enough from their owne writings, and the teſtimony of others concerning them. But <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> whom I have above quoted, ſpeaking of their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom I now cite for this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, <hi>viz. Keplar</hi> and <hi>Galilaeus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De phaenom. lunae. c.</hi> 4.</note> affirmes that to his knowledge they did but jeſt in thoſe things which they write concerning this, and as for any ſuch world, he aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:28034:47"/> knowes they never ſo much as dreamt of it. But I had rather believe their owne words, then his pretended knowledge.</p>
               <p>'Tis true indeed, in many things they doe but trifle, but for the maine ſcope of thoſe diſcourſes, 'tis as manifeſt they ſeriouſly meant it, as any indifferent Reader may eaſily diſcerne; otherwiſe ſure <hi>Campanella</hi> (a man as well acquainted with his opinion, and perhaps his perſon as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was) would never have writ an apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for him. And beſides 'tis very likely if it had beene but a jeſt, <hi>Galilaeus</hi> would never have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo much for it as afterwards he did. But as for the knowledge which hee pretends, you may gueſſe what it was by his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence (I ſay not preſumption) in other aſſertions, and his boldneſſe in them may well derogate from <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 7.</note> his credit in this. For ſpeaking of <hi>Ptolome's Hypotheſis</hi> he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this verdict, <hi>Impoſſibile eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centricorum</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:28034:47"/> 
                  <hi>&amp; epicyclorum poſitio, nec aliquus eſt ex Mathematicis adeo ſtultis qui veram illam exiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The poſition of <hi>Excen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trickes</hi> and <hi>Epicycles</hi> is altogether impoſſible, nor is there any Mathematician ſuch a foole as to thinke it true.</q> I ſhould gueſſe hee could not have knowledge enough to maintaine any other Hypotheſis who was ſo ignorant in Mathematickes, as to deny that any good Author held this. For I would faine know whether there were never any that thought the Heavens to be ſolid bodies, and that there were ſuch kindes of motion as is by thoſe feined Orbes ſupplied; if ſo, then <hi>Caeſar la Calla</hi> was much miſtaken. I thinke his aſſertions are equally true, that <hi>Galilaeus</hi> and <hi>Keplar</hi> did not hold this, and that there were none which ever held that other.</p>
               <p>But in my following diſcourſe I ſhall moſt inſiſt on the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> the inventor of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:28034:48"/> that famous perſpective, whereby we may diſcerne the Heavens hard by us, whereby thoſe things which others have formerly gueſt at are manifeſted to the eye, and plainely diſcovered beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception or doubt, of which admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable invention, theſe latter ages of the world may juſtly boaſt, and for this expect to be celebrated by poſterity. 'Tis related of <hi>Eudoxus,</hi> that hee wiſhed himſelfe burnt with <hi>Phaeton,</hi> ſo he might ſtand over the Sunne to contemplate its nature; had hee lived in theſe daies, hee might have enjoyed his wiſh at an eaſier rate, and ſcaling the heavens by this glaſſe, might plainely have diſcerned what hee ſo much deſired. <hi>Keplar</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoſe ſtrange diſcoveries which this perſpective had made, could not chooſe but cry out in a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and rapture of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>O multiſcium &amp; quovis ſceptro pretioſius perſpicillum! an qui te dextra tenet, ille non dominus</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:28034:48"/> 
                  <hi>conſtitnatur operum Dei?</hi> And <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De macula in ſole obſer.</note> 
                  <hi>Fabrieius</hi> an elegant wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſpeaking of the ſame glaſſe, and for this invention preferring our age before thoſe former times of greater ignorance, ſayes thus; <hi>Adeo ſumus ſuperiores veteribus, ut quam illi carminis magici pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciatu de miſſam repreſent âſſe putan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur nos non tantum innocenter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittamus, ſed etiam familiuri quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam intuitu ejus quaſi conditionem intueamur.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">So much are wee above the ancients, that whereas they were faine by their magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call charmes to repreſent the Moones approach, wee cannot onely bring her lower with a greater innocence, but may alſo with a more familiar view be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her condition.</q> And becauſe you ſhall have no occaſion to que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the truth of thoſe experiments, which I ſhall afterwards urge from it; I will therefore ſetdowne the teſtimony of an enemy, and ſuch a witneſſe hath alwaies beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:28034:49"/> prevalent: you may ſee it in the abovenamed <hi>Caeſar la</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De phaenom. cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Galla,</hi> whoſe words are theſe: <hi>Mercurium caduceum geſtantem, coeleſtia nunciare, &amp; mortuorum animas ab inferis revocare ſapiens finxit antiquitas. Galilaeum vero novum Jovis interpretem Teleſcopio caducaeo inſtructum Sydera aperire, &amp; veterum Philoſophorum manes ad ſuperos revocare ſolers noſtra aetas videt &amp; admiratur.</hi> Wiſe antiquity fabled <hi>Mercury</hi> carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a rodde in his hand to relate newes from Heaven, and call backe the ſoules of the dead, but it hath been the happineſſe of our induſtrious age to ſee and admire <hi>Galilaeus</hi> the new Embaſſadour of the Gods furniſhed with his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective to unfold the nature of the Starres, and awaken the ghoſts of the ancient Philoſophers. So worthily and highly did theſe men eſteeme of this excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention.</p>
               <p>Now if you would know what
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:28034:49"/> might bee done by this glaſſe, in the ſight of ſuch things as were neerer at hand, the ſame Authour will tell you, when he ſayes, that by it thoſe things which could <note place="margin">
                     <hi>ibid. c.</hi> 5.</note> ſcarce at all bee diſcerned by the eye at the diſtance of a mile and a halfe, might plainely and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly be perceived for 16 <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> miles, and that as they were really in themſelves, without any tranſpoſition or falſifying at all. So that what the ancient Poets were faine to put in a fable, our more happy age hath found out in a truth, and we may diſcerne as farre with theſe eyes which <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus</hi> hath beſtowed upon us, as <hi>Lynceus</hi> could with thoſe which the Poets attributed unto him. But if you yet doubt whether all theſe obſervations were true, the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 1.</note> ſame Author may confirme you, when he ſayes they were ſhewed, <hi>Non u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i aut alteri, ſed quamplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimis, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> gregariis hominibus, ſed praecipuis at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diſciplinis omnibus,</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:28034:50"/> 
                  <hi>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on Mathematicis &amp; opticis praeceptis, optimè inſtructis ſedulâ ac diligenti inſpectione.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Not to one or two, but to very many, and thoſe not ordinary men, but to thoſe who were well vers'd in Mathematickes and Opticks, and that not with a meere glance, but with a ſedulous and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent inſpection.</q> And leaſt any ſcruple might remaine unanſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, or you might thinke the men who beheld all this though they might be skilfull, yet they came with credulous minds, and ſo were more eaſie to be deluded. Hee addes that it was ſhewed, <hi>vires qui</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ad experimenta haec contradicendi animo acceſſerant.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">To ſuch as were come with a great deale of prejudice, and an intent of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction.</q> Thus you may ſee the certainety of thoſe experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which were taken by this glaſſe. I have ſpoken the more concerning it, becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſhall bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row many things in my farther
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:28034:50"/> diſcourſe, from thoſe diſcoveries which were made by it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> have now cited ſuch Authors both ancient and moderne, who have directly maintained the ſame opinion. <hi>I</hi> told you likewiſe in the propoſition that it might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be deduced from the tenents of others: ſuch were <hi>Ariſtarchus, Philolaus</hi> and <hi>Copernicus,</hi> with many other later writers who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to their hypotheſis, ſo <hi>Ioach. Rlelicus, David Origanus Lansbergius, Guil. Gilbert,</hi> and (if <hi>I</hi> may believe <hi>Campanella) Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meri</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Apologia pro Galilaeo.</note> 
                  <hi>alii Angli &amp; Galli.</hi> Very many others, both Engliſh and French, all who affirmed our Earth to bee one of the Planets, and the Sunne to be the Centre of all, about which the heavenly bodies did move, and how horid ſoever this may ſeeme at the firſt, yet is it likely enough to be true, nor is there any maxime or obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in Opticks (ſaith <hi>Pena)</hi> that can diſprove it.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:28034:51"/>
               <p> Now if our earth were one of the Planets (as it is according to them) then why may not another of the Planets be an earth?</p>
               <p>Thus have <hi>I</hi> ſhewed you the truth of this propoſition: Before <hi>I</hi> proceede farther, 'tis requiſite that <hi>I</hi> informe the Reader, what method <hi>I</hi> ſhall follow in the proving of this chiefe aſſertion, that there is a World in the Moone.</p>
               <p>The order by which <hi>I</hi> ſhall be guided will be that which <hi>Ariſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>à</hi> 10. <hi>cap. ad</hi> 10m.</note> uſes in his booke <hi>De mundo</hi> (if that booke were his.)</p>
               <p>Firſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> of thoſe chiefe parts which are in it; not the elementary and aethereall (as he doth there) ſince this doth not belong to the elementary contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, but of the Sea and Land, &amp;c. Secondly, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of thoſe things which are extrinſecall to it, as the ſeaſons, meteors and inhabitants.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="proposition">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:28034:51"/>
               <head>Propoſition 7. <hi>That thoſe ſpots and brighter parts which by our ſight may bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in the Moone, doe ſhew the difference betwixt the Sea and Land in that other World.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr the cleare proofe of this propoſition, I ſhall firſt rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon up and refute the opinions of others concerning the matter and forme of thoſe ſpots, and then ſhew the greater probability of this preſent aſſertion, and how agreeable it is to that truth, which is moſt commonly received; as for the opinions of other concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe, they have beene very many, I will only reckon up thoſe which are common and remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <p>Some there are that thinke thoſe ſpots doe not ariſe from any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:28034:52"/> of the parts, but a deceit of the eye, which cannot at ſuch a diſtance diſcerne an equall light in that planet, but theſe doe but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay it, and ſhew not any reaſon for the proofe of their opinion: Others thinke that there are ſome bodies betwixt the Sunne and Moone, which keeping off the <note place="margin">So <hi>Bede</hi> in <hi>li. de Mund. conſtit.</hi>
                  </note> lights in ſome parts, doe by their ſhadow produce theſe ſpots which we there diſcerne.</p>
               <p>Others would have them to be the figure of the mountaines here below repreſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted there as in a loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king-glaſſe. But none of thoſe fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies can be true, becauſe the ſpots are ſtill the ſame, and not varied according to the difference of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and beſides, <hi>Cardan</hi> thinks it is impoſſible that any image ſhould <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De ſubtil. lib.</hi> 3.</note> be conveyed ſo farre as there to be repreſented unto us at ſuch a diſtance, but tis commonly related of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> that he by writing, what he pleaſed in a glaſſe, by the reflexio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſame ſpecies, would
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:28034:52"/> make thoſe letters to appeare in the circle of the Moone, where they ſhould be legible by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who might at that time be ſome miles diſtant from him. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Occulta-ad Philoſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa</hi> affirmes this to be poſſible, and the way of performing it not unknowne to himſelfe, with ſome others in his time. It may be that our Biſhop did by the like meanes performe thoſe ſtrange concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which hee profeſſes in his <hi>Nuncius inanimatus,</hi> where hee pretends that hee can informe his friends of what he pleaſes, though they be an hundred miles diſtant, <hi>forte etiam, vel miliare milleſimum,</hi> they are his owne words, and, perhaps, a thouſand, and all this in a minutes ſpace, or little more, quicker than the Sunne can move.</p>
               <p>Now, what conveyance there ſhould be for ſo ſpeedy a paſſage, I cannot conceive, unleſſe it be carried with the light, then which wee know not any thing quicker; but of this onely by the way;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:28034:53"/> however, whether thoſe images can be repreſented ſo or not, yet certaine it is, thoſe ſpots are not ſuch repreſentations. Some thinke that when God had at firſt created too much earth to make a perfect globe, not knowing well where to beſtow the reſt, he placed it in the Moone, which ever ſince hath ſo darkened it in ſome parts, but the impiety of this is ſufficient con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation, ſince it ſo much detracts from the divine power and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>The <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut. de placit. phil. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> Stoicks held that Planet to be mixed of fire and aire, and in their opinion, the variety of its compoſition, cauſed her ſpots: <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> thought all the ſtarres to be of an earthly nature, mixed with ſome fire, and as for the Sunne, he affirmed it to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a fiery ſtone; for which later opinion, the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> l.</hi> 2. <hi>con. App. Auguſt. de Civit. Dei. l.</hi> 18. <hi>c.</hi> 41.</note> ſentenc'd him to death; thoſe zealous Idolaters counting it a great blaſphemy, to make their
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:28034:53"/> God a ſtone, whereas notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, they were ſo ſenſleſſe in their adoration of Idols, as to make a ſtone their God, this <hi>Anaxagoras</hi> affirmed the Moone to be more terreſtriall then the other, but of a greater purity then any thing here below, and the ſpots hee thought were nothing elſe, but ſome cloudy parts, intermingled with the light which belonged to that Planet, but I have above de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the ſuppoſition on which this fancy is grounded: <hi>Pliny</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. Hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> thinkes they ariſe from ſome droſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie ſtuffe, mixed with that moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture which the Moone attracts unto her ſelfe, but hee was of their opinion who thought the ſtarres were nouriſhed by ſome earthly vapours, which you may commonly ſee refuted in the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators</hi> on the bookes, <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Coelo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vitellio</hi> and <hi>Reinoldus</hi> affirme <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Opt. lib.</hi> 9. <hi>comment. in Purb. pag.</hi> 164.</note> the ſpots to be the thicket parts of the Moone, into which the Sunne cannot infuſe much light,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:28034:54"/> and this (ſay they) is the reaſon, why in the Sunnes eclipſes, the ſpots and brighter parts are ſtill in ſome meaſure diſtinguiſhed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Sunne beames are not able ſo well to penetrate through thoſe thicker, as they may through the thinner parts of that Planet. Of this opinion alſo was <hi>Caeſar la Galla,</hi> whoſe words are theſe, <q rend="margQuotes">The Moone doth there appeare <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ex qua par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te luna eſt tranſpicua nonſolum ſecundum ſuperficiem, ſed etiam ſecundum ſubſtantiam, eatenus cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, ex qua autem parte opaca eſt, ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenus obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra videtur. De Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nom. cap.</hi> 11.</note> cleareſt, where ſhee is tranſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous, not onely through the ſuperficies, but the ſubſtance alſo, and there ſhe ſeemes ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, where her body is moſt opacous.</q> The ground of this his aſſertion was, becauſe hee thought the Moone did receive and beſtow her light by illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination onely, and not at all by reflexion, but this, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the ſuppoſed pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of the Sunne beames, and the perſpicuity of the Moones body I have above anſwered and refuted.</p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:28034:54"/>
               <p> The more common and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall opinion is, that the ſpots are <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Albert. mag. de Coaevis. Q.</hi> 4. <hi>Art.</hi> 21. <hi>Colleg. Con.</hi>
                  </note> the thinner parts of the Moone, which are leſſe able to reflect the beames that they receive from the Sunne, and this is moſt agreeable to reaſon; for if the ſtarres are therefore brighteſt, becauſe they are thicker and more ſolid then their orbes, then it will follow, that thoſe parts of the Moone which have leſſe light, have alſo leſſe thickeneſſe. It was the providence of nature (ſay ſome) that ſo contrived that planet to have theſe ſpots within it, for ſince that is neereſt to thoſe lower bodies which are ſo full of defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, 'tis requiſite that it ſhould in ſome meaſure agree with them, and as in this inferiour world the higher bodies are the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat, ſo alſo in the heavens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is aſcended unto by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and the Moone being the loweſt, muſt be the leaſt pure, and <note place="margin">De Somniis.</note> therefore <hi>Philo</hi> the Jew interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:28034:55"/> 
                  <hi>Iacobs</hi> dreame concerning the ladder, doth in an allegory ſhew, how that in the fabricke of the world, all things grow perfecter as they grow higher, and this is the reaſon (ſaith hee) why the Moone doth not conſiſt of any pure ſimple matter, but is mixed with aire, which ſhewes ſo darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly within her body.</p>
               <p>But this cannot be a ſufficient reaſon, for though it were true that nature did frame every thing perfecter as it was higher, yet is it as true that nature frames every thing fully perfect for that office to which ſhee intends it. Now, had ſhe intended the Moone meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to reflect the Sunne beames and give light, the ſpots then had not ſo much argued her providence, as her unskilfulneſſe and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if in the haſte of her worke <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scalig. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit.</hi> 62.</note> ſhee could not tell how to make that body exactly fit, for that office to which ſhe appointed it.</p>
               <p>Tis likely then that ſhe had ſome
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:28034:55"/> other end which moved her to produce this variety, and this in all probability was her intent to make it a fit body for habitation with the ſame conveniences of ſea and land, as this inferiour world doth partake of. For ſince the Moone is ſuch a vaſt, ſuch a ſolid and opacous body like our earth (as was above proved) why may it not be probable, that thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and thicker parts appearing in her doe ſhew the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſea and land in that other world; and <hi>Galilaeus</hi> doubts not, but that if our earth were viſible at the ſame diſtance, there would be the like appearance of it.</p>
               <p>As for the forme of thoſe ſpots, ſome of the vulgar thinke they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent a man, and the Poets gueſſe tis the boy <hi>Endimion,</hi> whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ſhe loves ſo well, that ſhee carries him with her, others will have it onely to be the face of a man as the Moone is uſually pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but <hi>Albertus</hi> thinkes rather,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:28034:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:28034:56"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:28034:57"/> that it repreſents a Lyon with his taile towards the Eaſt, and his head the Weſt, and <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſcbius Nioremb. Hiſt. Nat. lib.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 15.</note> ſome others have thought it to be very much like a Fox, &amp; certainly 'tis, as much like a Lyon as that in the <hi>Zodiake,</hi> or as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſa major</hi> is like a Beare.</p>
               <p>I ſhould gueſſe that it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents one of theſe as well as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and any thing elſe as well as any of theſe, ſince 'tis but a ſtrong imagination, which fancies ſuch images as ſchoole-boyes uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual'y do in the markes of a wall, whereas there is not any ſuch ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude in the ſpots themſelves, which rather like our Sea, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the land, appeares under a rugged and confuſed figure, and do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h not repreſent any diſtinct image, ſo that both in reſpect of the matter and the forme it may be probable enough, that thoſe ſpots and brighter parts may ſhew the diſtinction betwixt the Sea and Land in that other world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="proposition">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:28034:57"/>
               <head>Propoſition. 8. <hi>The ſpots repreſent the Sea, and the brighter parts the Land.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen I firſt compared the nature of our earth and water with thoſe appearances in the Moone; I concluded contrary to the propoſition, that the brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter parts repreſented the water, and the ſpots the land; of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion likewiſe was <hi>Keplar</hi> at the firſt, but my ſecond thoughts, and the reading of others, have now <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Opt. Aſtro. c.</hi> 6. <hi>num.</hi> 9. <hi>Diſſert. cum nuncio Gal.</hi>
                  </note> convinced me (as after he was) of the truth of that propoſition which I have now ſee downe. But before I come to the confirmation of it, I ſhall mention thoſe ſeruples which at firſt made mee doubt of the truth of this opinion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It may be objected, 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, if there be any ſuch ſea and land as ours, that it bears ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and ſimilitude with ours: but now this propoſition takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:28034:58"/> all likeneſſe betwixt them, for whereas the ſuperficies of our earth is but the third part of the whole ſurface in the globe, two parts being overſpread with the water (as <hi>Scaliger</hi> obſerves) yet here according to this opinion, the <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exercit.</hi> 38.</note> Sea ſhould be leſſe then the land, ſince there is not ſo much of the beſpotted, as there is of the enligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tened parts, wherfore 'tis probable, that either there is no ſuch thing at all, or elſe that the brighter parts are the Sea.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The water, by reaſon of the ſmoothneſſe of its ſuperficies, ſeemes better able to reflect the Sun beames then the earth, which in moſt places is ſo full of rugged<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of graſſe and trees, and ſuch like impediments of reflexion, and beſides, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon experience ſhewes, that the water ſhines with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more glorious brightneſſe then the earth, therefore it ſhould ſeeme that the ſpots are the earth, and the brighter parts the water.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:28034:58"/>
               <p> But to the firſt it may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered.</p>
               <p n="1">1. There is no great probability in this conſequence, that becauſe 'tis ſo with us, therefore it muſt be ſo with the parts of the Moone, for ſince there is ſuch a difference betwixt them in divers other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, they may not perhaps agree in this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That aſſertion of <hi>Sculiger</hi> is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Meteoris l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Art.</hi> 1.</note> not by all granted for a truth. <hi>Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondus</hi> with others thinke that the ſuperficies of the Sea and Land in ſo much of the world as is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy diſcovered is equall and of the ſame extenſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Orbe of thicke and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porous ayer which incompaſſes the Moone, makes the brighter parts of that Planet appeare big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then in themſelves they are; as I ſhall ſhew afterwards.</p>
               <p>To the ſecond it may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that though the water be of a ſmooth ſuperficies, and ſo may ſeeme moſt fit to reverberate the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:28034:59"/> light, yet becauſe 'tis of a perſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous nature, therefore the beames muſt ſinke into it, and cannot ſo ſtrongly and clearely be reflected. <hi>Sicut in ſpeculo ubi plumbum abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum fuerit,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cardan)</hi> as in Looking-glaſſes where part of the lead is razed of, and nothing left behind to reverberate the image, the ſpecies muſt there paſſe through and not backe againe; ſo it is where the beames penetrate and ſinke into the ſubſtance of the body, there cannot be ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate and ſtrong reflexion as when they are beate backe from the ſuperficies, and therefore the Sunne cauſes a greater heate by farre upon the Land then upon the water. Now as for that experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment where tis ſayd, that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have a greater brightneſſe then the Land: I anſwere, 'tis true onely there where they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the image of the Sunne or ſome bright cloud, and not in other places, as is very
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:28034:59"/> plaine by common obſervation.</p>
               <p>So that notwithſtanding thoſe doubts, yet this propoſition may remaine true, that the ſpots may be the Sea, and the brighter parts the Land. Of this opinion was <hi>Plutarch:</hi> unto him aſſented <hi>Kep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> and <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> whoſe words are theſe, <hi>Si quis veterum Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goreorum ſententiam exuſcitare</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De facielun. Diſſertatio. Nunc. Syd.</note> 
                  <hi>velit, lunam ſcilicet eſſe quaſi tellu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem alteram, ejus pars lucidior ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renam ſuperficiem, obſcurior verò aqueam magis congruè repraeſentet Mihi autem dubium fuit nunquam terreſtris globi à longè conſpecti, at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aradiis ſolaribus perfuſi, terream ſuperficiem clariorem, obſcuriorem vero aqueam ſeſe in conſpectum daturam.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If any man have a mind to renue the opinion of the <hi>Pythagoreans,</hi> that the Moone is another earth, then her brighter parts may fitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the earths ſuperficies, and the darker part the water: and for my part, I never doubted
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:28034:60"/> but that our earthly globe being ſhined upon by the Sunne, and beheld at a great diſtance, the Land would appeare brighteſt and the Sea more obſcurely.</q> The reaſons may be</p>
               <p n="1">1. That which I urged about the foregoing chapter, becauſe the water is the thinner part, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt give leſſe light.</p>
               <p n="2">2, Becauſe obſervation tels us, that the ſpotted parts are alwaies ſmooth and equall, having every where an equality of light when once they are enlightned by the Sunne, whereas the brighter parts are full of rugged gibboſities and mountaines having many ſhades in them, as I ſhall ſhew more at large afterwards.</p>
               <p>That in this Planet there muſt be Seas, <hi>Campanella</hi> indeavours to <note place="margin">Apologia pro Galilaeo.</note> prove out of Scripture interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>the waters above the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſpoken of in <hi>Geneſis</hi> to bee meant of the Sea in this world. For (ſaith he) 'tis not likely that
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:28034:60"/> there are any ſuch waters above the Orbes to moderate that heate which they receive from their ſwift motion (as ſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers thinke) nor did <hi>Moſes</hi> meane the Angels which may be called <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſſion. l.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 32.</note> ſpirituall waters, as <hi>Origen</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> would have it, for both theſe are rejected by the generall conſent: Nor could he meane any waters in the ſecond region, as moſt Commentators interpret it. For firſt there is nothing but va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours, which though they are afterwards turned into water, yet while they remaine there, they are onely the matter of that ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which may as well be fire or earth or ayre. 2. Thoſe vapours are not above the expanſum but in it. So that hee thinkes there is no other way to ſalve all, but by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Planets ſeverall worlds with Sea &amp; Land with ſuch Rivers and Springs as we have here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: Eſpecially ſince <hi>Eſdras</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Eſdr. 4. 7.</note> ſpeakes of the ſprings above the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:28034:61"/> Firmament, but I cannot agree with him in this, nor doe I thinke that any ſuch thing can be proved out of Scripture.</p>
               <p>Before I proceede to the next poſition, I ſhall firſt anſwer ſome doubts which might be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the generalitie of this truth, whereby it may ſeeme impoſſible that there ſhould be either Sea or Land in the Moone; for ſince ſhe moves ſo ſwiftly as Aſtronomers obſerve, why then does there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fall from her, or why doth ſhee not ſhake ſomething out by the celerity of her revolution? I anſwere, you muſt know that the inclination of every heavy body to its proper Center doth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently tie it unto its place, ſo that ſuppoſe any thing were ſeparated, yet muſt it neceſſarily returne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and there is no more danger of their falling into our world then there is feare of our falling into the Moone.</p>
               <p>But yet there are many fabulous
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:28034:61"/> relations of ſuch things as have dropped thence. There is a tale of the Nemean Lyon that <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> ſlew, which firſt ruſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the heards out of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne den in the Mountaine of <hi>Cytheron</hi> in <hi>Boeotia,</hi> the credulous people thought he was ſent from their Goddeſſe the Moone. And if a whirle-winde did chance to ſnatch any thing up, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards raine it downe againe, the ignorant multitude are apt to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that it dropt from Heaven. Thus <hi>Avicenna</hi> relates the ſtory of a Calfe which fell downe in a ſtorme, the beholders thinking it a Moon-calfe, and that it fell thence. So <hi>Cardan</hi> travelling upon the Apennine Mountaines, a ſudden blaſt tooke off his hat, which if it had beene carryed farre, he thinks the peaſants who had perceived it to fall, would have ſworne it had rained hats. After ſome ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner many of our prodigies come to paſſe, and the people are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:28034:62"/> to believe any thing, which they may relate to others as a very ſtrange and wonderfull event. I doubt not but the Trojan <hi>Palladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> the Romane <hi>Minerva,</hi> and our Ladies Church at <hi>Loretto,</hi> with many ſacred reliques preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Papiſts might droppe from the Moone as well as any of theſe.</p>
               <p>But it may be againe objected, ſuppoſe there were a bullet ſhot up in that world, would not the Moone runne away from it, before it could fall downe, ſince the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her body (being every day round our earth) is farre ſwifter than the other, and ſo the bullet muſt be left behind, and at length fall downe to us. To this I anſwer,</p>
               <p n="1">1. If a bullet could bee ſhot ſo farre till it came to the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of thoſe things which belong to our center, then it would fall downe to us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though there were ſome
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:28034:62"/> heavie body a great height in that ayer, yet would the motion of its center by an attractive vertue ſtill holds it within its convenient di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, ſo that whether their earth moved or ſtood ſtill, yet would the ſame violence caſt a body from it equally farre. That I may the plainer expreſſe my meaning, I will ſet downe this Diagramme.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:28034:63"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of Earth, magnetic field, and orbit</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Suppoſe this earth were A, which was to move in the circle C, D. and let the bullet be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at B. within its proper verge; I ſay, whether this earth did ſtand ſtil or move ſwiftly towards D, yet the bullet would ſtill keepe at the ſame diſtance by reaſon of that Magneticke vertue of the center (if I may ſo ſpeake) whereby all things within its ſpheare are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:28034:63"/> with it. So that the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence to the bullet, being nothing elſe but that whereby 'tis remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from its center, therefore an equall violence can carry a body from its proper place, but at an equall diſtance whether or no the center ſtand ſtill or move.</p>
               <p>The impartiall Reader may finde ſufficient ſatisfaction for this and ſuch other arguments as may be urged againſt the motion of that earth in the writings of <hi>Coperni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> and his followers, unto whom for brevities ſake I will referre them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="proposition">
               <head>Propoſition 9. <hi>That there are high Mountaines, deepe vallies, and ſpacious plaines in the body of the Moone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough there are ſome who thinke Mountaines to bee a deformity to the earth, as if they
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:28034:64"/> were either beate up by the flood, or elſe caſt up like ſo many heaps of rubbiſh left at the creation, yet if well conſidered, they will bee found as much to conduce to the beauty and conveniency of the univerſe as any of the other parrs. Nature (ſaith <hi>Pliny)</hi> purpoſely <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. hiſt. l.</hi> 36. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> framed them for many excellent uſes: partly to tame the violence of greater Rivers, to ſtrengthen certaine joynts within the veines and bowels of the earth, to break the force of the Seas inundation, and for the ſafety of the earths inhabitants, whether beaſts or men. That they make much for the protection of beaſts the Pſalmiſt <note place="margin">Pſal. 104. v. 18.</note> teſtifies, <hi>The higheſt hils are a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge for the wild goates, and the rockes for conies.</hi> The Kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet had learned the ſafety of theſe by his owne experience, when hee alſo was faine to make a mountaine his refuge from the fury of his Maſter <hi>Saul,</hi> who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted him in the wilderneſſe.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:28034:64"/>
               <p> True indeed, ſuch places as theſe keepe their neighbours poore, as being moſt barren, but yet they preſerve them ſafe, as being moſt ſtrong, witneſſe our unconquered <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt protection hath beene the naturall ſtrength of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſo fortified with Mountaines, that theſe have alwaies beene unto them ſure retraites from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and oppreſſion of others, wherefore a good Authour doth rightly call them natures bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warkes caſt up at God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties owne charges, the ſcornes and, curbes of victorious armies, which made the Barbarians in <hi>Curtius</hi> ſo confident of their owne ſafety, when they were once retired to an inacceſſible mountaine, that when <hi>Alexanders</hi> Legate had brought them to a parley and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading them to yeeld, told them of his maſters victories, what Seas and Wilderneſſes he had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, they replied that all that might
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:28034:65"/> be, but could <hi>Alexander</hi> fly too? Over the Seas he might have ſhips, and over the land horſes, but hee muſt have wings before hee could get up thither. Such ſafety did thoſe barbarous nations conceive in the mountaines whereunto they were retyred, certainly then ſuch uſefull parts were not the effect of mans ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, or produced by the Worlds cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe the flood, but rather at the firſt created by the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and providence of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty.</p>
               <p>So that if I intend to prove that the Moone is ſuch a habitable world as this is, 'tis requiſite that I ſhew it to have the ſame conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences of habitation as this hath, and here if ſome Rabbi or Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick were to handle the point they would firſt prove it out of Scripture, from that place in <hi>Moſes</hi> his bleſſing, where hee <note place="margin">Deut. 33. 15.</note> ſpeakes of the ancient moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and laſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng hills, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:28034:65"/> for having immediately before mentioned thoſe bleſſings which ſhould happen unto <hi>Joſeph</hi> by the influence of the Moone, he does preſently exegetically iterate them in bleſſing him with the chiefe things of the ancient mountaines and laſting hills; you may alſo ſee the ſame expreſſion uſed in <hi>Iacobs</hi> bleſſing of <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 49. 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But however we may deale <hi>pro</hi> or <hi>con</hi> in Philoſophy, yet we muſt not j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt with divine truths, or bring Scripture to patronize any fancy of our owne, though, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, it be a truth. For the better proofe of this propoſition, I might here cite the teſtimony of <hi>Diodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> who thought the Moone to be full of rugged places, <hi>vel ut terreſtribus tumulis ſupercilioſam,</hi> but he erred much in ſome circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this opinion, eſpicially where hee ſaies, there is an Iland amongſt the <hi>Hyperboreans,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thoſe hills may to the eye be plainly diſcovered, and for this
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:28034:66"/> reaſon <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lect. aut l.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. <hi>Plut. de plac. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Caelius</hi> calls him a fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Writer, but you may ſee more expreſſe authority for the proofe of this in the opinions of <hi>Anaxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras</hi> and <hi>Democritus,</hi> who held that this Planet was full of cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion grounds, mountains and val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De coelo. l.</hi> 2. <hi>part.</hi> 49.</note> and this ſeemed likewiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable unto <hi>Auguſtinus Nifus,</hi> whoſe words are theſe: <hi>Forſitan non eſt remotum dicere lunae partes eſſe diverſas, veluti ſunt partes ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae, quarum aliae ſunt valloſae, aliae montoſae, ex quarum differentia ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici pot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt facies illa lunae; nec eſt rae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni diſſonum, nam luna eſt corpus imperfectè Sphaericum, cum ſit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ab ultimo coelo elongatum, ut ſupra dixit Ariſtoteles.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Perhaps, it would not be amiſſe to ſay that the parts of the Moone were divers, as the parts of this earth, whereof ſome are vallies, and ſome mountaines, from the difference of which, ſome ſpots in the Moone may proceed; nor is this againſt reaſon, for that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:28034:66"/> Planet cannot be perfectly ſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall, ſince 'tis ſo remote a bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> from the firſt orbe, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> had ſaid before.</q> You may ſee this truth aſſented unto by <hi>Blanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Mundi fab. pars</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> the Jeſuit, and by him confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with divers reaſons. <hi>Keplar</hi> hath obſerved in the Moones <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aſtron. Opt. c.</hi> 6. <hi>num.</hi> 9</note> eclipſes, that the diviſion of her inlightened part from the ſhaded, was made by a crooked unequall line, of which there cannot be any probable cauſe conceived, unleſſe it did ariſe from the ruggedneſſe of that planet, for it cannot at all be produc'd from the ſhade of any mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains here upon earth, becauſe theſe would be ſo leſſened before they could reach ſo high in a coni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ſhadow, that they would not be at all ſenſible unto us (as might eaſily be demonſtrated) nor can it be conceived what reaſon of this difference there ſhould be in the Sunne. Wherefore there being no other body that hath any thing to doe in eclipſes, we muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:28034:67"/> conclude, that it is cauſed by a variety of parts in the Moone it ſelfe, and what can there be but its gibboſities? Now if you ſhould aske a reaſon why there ſhould be ſuch a multitude of theſe in that Planet, the ſame <hi>Keplar</hi> ſhall jeſt you out an anſwer, for ſuppoſing (ſaith hee) thoſe inhabitants are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gger than any of us in the ſame proportion, as their daies are lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than ours, vix. by fifteen times it may be for want of ſtones to erect ſuch vaſt houſes as were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for their bodies, they are faine to digge great and round hollowes in the earth, where they may both procure water for their thirſt, and turning about with the ſhade, may avoid thoſe great heats which otherwiſe they would be liable unto; or if you will give <hi>Caeſar la Galla</hi> leave to gueſſe in the ſame manner, he would rather think that thoſe thirſty nations caſt up ſo many and ſo great heaps of earth in digging of their wine cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:28034:67"/> but this onely by the way.</p>
               <p>I ſhall next produce the eye witneſſe of <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> on which I <note place="margin">Nuncius Sydereus.</note> moſt of all depend for the proofe of this Propoſition, when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the new Moone through his perſpective it appeared to him under a rugged &amp; ſpotted figure, ſeeming to have the darker and enlightned parts divided by a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous line, having ſome parcells of light at a good diſtance from the other, and this difference is ſo remarkable, that you may eaſily perceive it through one of thoſe ordinary perſpectives, which are commonly ſold amongſt us, but for your better apprehending of what I deliver, I will ſet downe the Figure as I find it in <hi>Galilaeus:</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:28034:68"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of Moon</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Suppoſe A B C D to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the appearande of the Moones body being in a ſextile, you may ſee ſome brighter parts ſeparated at a pretty diſtance from the other, which can be nothing elſe but a reflexion of the Sunne beames up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome parts that are higher then the reſt, and thoſe obſcure gibbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:28034:68"/> which ſtand out towards the enlightened parts muſt be ſuch hollow and deepe places where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the rayes cannot reach, but when the Moone is got farther off from the Sunne, and come to that fulneſſe, as this line B D doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent her under, then doe theſe parts alſo receive an equall light, excepting onely that difference which doth appeare betwixt their ſea and land. And if you do conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how any rugged body would appeare, being enlightened, you would eaſily conceive that it muſt neceſſarily ſeeme under ſome ſuch gibbous unequall forme, as the Moone is here repreſented. Now for the infalibility of theſe appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances, I ſhall referre the reader to that which hath beene ſaid in the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Propoſition.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Caeſar la Galla</hi> affirmes, that all theſe appearances may conſaſt with a plaine ſuperficies, if wee ſuppoſe the parts of the body to be ſome of them, <hi>Diaphanous,</hi> and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:28034:69"/> ſome opacous; and if you object that the light which is convayed to any diaphanous part in a plaine ſuperficies muſt be by a continued line, whereas here there appeare many brighter parts among the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure at ſome diſtance from the reſt. To this hee anſwers, it may ariſe from ſome ſecret conveiances and channels within her body, that doe conſiſt of a more diaphanous matter which being covered over with an opacous ſuperficies, the light paſſing through them may breake out a great way off, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the other parts betwixt may ſtill remaine darke. Juſt as the River <hi>Arethuſa</hi> in <hi>Sicily</hi> which runnes under ground for a great way, and afterwards breakes out againe. But becauſe this is one of the chiefeſt fancies whereby hee thinkes hee hath fully anſwered the arguments of this opinion, I will therefore ſet downe his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere in his owne words, leaſt the Reader might ſuſpect more in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:28034:69"/> them then I have expreſſed. <hi>Non</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>eſt impoſſibile coecos ductus diaphani &amp; perſpicui corporis, ſed opacd ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficie protendi, uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in diaphanam aliquam ex profundo in ſuperficiem, emergentem partem, per quos ductus lumen longo poſtmodum interſtitio erumpat, &amp;c.</hi> But I reply, if the ſuperficies betwixt theſe two en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened parts remaine darke becauſe of its opacity, then would it alwaies be darke, and the Sunne could not make it partake of light more then it could of perſpicuity: But this contradicts all experience as you may ſee in <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> who affirmes that when the Sunne comes nearer to his oppoſition, then that which is betwixt them, both is enlightned as well as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Nay this oppoſes his owne eye-witneſſe, for he confeſſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that he ſaw this by the glaſſe. He had ſaid before that he came to ſee thoſe ſtrange ſights diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by <hi>Galilaeus</hi> his glaſſe with an intent of contradiction, and you
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:28034:70"/> may reade that confirmed in the weakeneſſe of this anſwere, which rather bewrayes an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate then a perſwaded will, for otherwiſe ſure hee would never have undertooke to have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch certaine proofes with ſo groundleſſe a fancy.</p>
               <p>But it may bee objected, that '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is almoſt impoſſible, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlikely that in the Moone there ſhould be any mountaines ſo high as thoſe obſervations make them, for doe but ſuppoſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the common principles, that the Moones diameter unto the Earths is very neere to the proportion of 2. to 7, ſuppoſe withall that the Earths diameter containes about 7000 Italian miles, and the Moones 2000 (as is commonly granted) now <hi>Gali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laeus</hi> hath obſerved that ſome parts have been enlightened when they were the twentieth part of the diameter diſtant from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon terme of illumination, ſo that
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:28034:70"/> hence it muſt neceſſarily follow that there may bee ſome Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in the Moone ſo high, that they are able to caſt a ſhadow a 100 miles off. An opinion that ſounds like a prodigie or a fiction; wherefore 'tis likely that either thoſe appearances are cauſed by ſomewhat elſe beſides mountaines, or elſe thoſe are fallible obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, from whence may follow ſuch improbable inconceiveable conſequences.</p>
               <p>But to this I anſwere:</p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt conſider the heighr of the Mountaines is but very little, if you compare them to the length of their ſhadowes. S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. §. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Rawleigh</hi> obſerves that the Mount <hi>Athes</hi> now called <hi>Lacas</hi> caſts its ſhadow 300 furlongs, which is above 37 miles, and yet that Mount is none of the higheſt, nay <hi>Solinus</hi> (whom I ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Poly. hiſtor. c.</hi> 21.</note> believe in this kinde) affirmes that this Mountaine gives his ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow quite over the Sea, from
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:28034:71"/> 
                  <hi>Macedon</hi> to the Ile of <hi>Lemnos</hi> which is 700 furlongs or 84 miles, and yet according to the common reckoning it doth ſcarce reach 4 miles upwards, in its perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar height.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I affirme that there are very high Mountaines in the Moone. <hi>Keplar</hi> and <hi>Galilaeus</hi> thinke that they are higher than any which are upon our earth. But I am not of their opinion in this, becauſe I ſuppoſe they goe upon a falſe ground whilſt they conceive that the higheſt mountaine upon the earth is not above a mile perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular.</p>
               <p>Whereas 'tis the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and found true enough by obſervation, that <hi>Olympus, Atlas, Taurus</hi> and <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> with many others are much above this height. <hi>Tenariffa</hi> in the Canary Ilands is proved by computation to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 8 miles perpendicular, and about this height is the mount <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7. §. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Perjacaca</hi> in <hi>America:</hi> S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Walter</hi>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:28034:71"/> 
                  <hi>Rawleigh</hi> ſeeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to thinke, that the higheſt of theſe is neere 30 miles upright: nay <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Meteor. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> of <hi>Caucaſus</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> affirmes it to bee viſible for 560 miles, as ſome interpreters finde by compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, from which it will follow, that it was 78 miles perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly high, as you may ſee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comparatio Ariſt. cum Platone Sect.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> by <hi>Jacobus Mazonius,</hi> and out of him in <hi>Blancanus</hi> the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite. But this deviates from the truth more in exceſſe then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Expoſi. in loc. Math. Arlis. loc.</hi> 148.</note> doth in defect. However though theſe in the moone are not ſo high as ſome amongſt us, yet certaine it is they are of a great height, and ſome of them at the leaſt foure miles perpendicular. This I ſhall prove from the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> whoſe glaſſe can ſhew this truth to the ſenſes, a proofe beyond exception and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that man muſt needs be of a moſt timerous faith who dares not believe his owne eye.</p>
               <p>By that perſpective you may
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:28034:72"/> plainely diſcerne ſome enlightned parts (which are the mountaines) to be diſtant from the other about the twentieth part of the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. From whence it will follow, that thoſe mountaines muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be at the leaſt foure Italian miles in height.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of Moon</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>For let BDEF be the body of the moone, ABC will be a ray or beame of the Sunne, which enlightens a mountaine at A and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:28034:72"/> 
                  <hi>B</hi> is the point of contingency, the diſtance betwixt A and B muſt bee ſuppoſed to be the twentieth part of the diameter which is an 100 miles, for ſo far are ſome enlighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned parts ſevered from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon terme of illumination. Now the aggregate of the quadrate from A <hi>B</hi> a hundred, and <hi>B G</hi> a 1000 will bee 1010000, unto which the quadra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ariſing from A G muſt be equall according to the 47<hi rend="sup">th</hi> propoſition in the firſt booke of elements. Therefore the whole line <hi>A G</hi> is ſomewhat more than 104, and the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance betwixt H A muſt be above 4 miles, which was the thing to be proved.</p>
               <p>But it may be againe objected, if there be ſuch rugged parts, and ſo high mountaines, why then cannot wee diſcerne them at this diſtance, why doth the moone ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare unto us ſo exactly round, and not rather as a wheele with teeth?</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:28034:73"/>
               <p> I anſwere, by reaſon of too great a diſtance, for if the whole body appeare to our eye ſo little, then thoſe parts which beare ſo ſmall a proportion to the whole will not at all be ſenſible.</p>
               <p>But it may be replied, if there were any ſuch remarkeable hils, why does not the limbe of the moone appeare like a wheele with teeth to thoſe who looke upon it through the great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective on whoſe witneſſe you ſo much depend? or what reaſon is there that ſhe appeares as exactly round through it as ſhee doth to the bare eye? certainely then either there is no ſuch thing as you ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, or elſe the glaſſe failes much in this diſcovery.</p>
               <p>To this I ſhall anſwere out of <hi>Galilaeus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. You muſt know that there is not meerely one ranke of moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines about the edge of the moone, but divers orders, one mountaine behind another, and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:28034:73"/> ſo there is ſomewhat to hinder thoſe void ſpaces which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, perhaps, might appeare.</p>
               <p>Now where there be many hils, the ground ſeemes even to a man that can ſee the tops of all. Thus when the ſea rages, and many vaſt waves are lifted up, yet all may appeare plaine enough to one that ſtands at the ſhore. So where there are ſo many hils, the inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity will be leſſe remarkable, if it be diſcerned at a diſtance.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though there be mountains in that part which appeares unto us, to be the limbe of the Moone, as well as in any other place, yet the bright vapours hide their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance: for there is an orbe of thicke vaporous aire that doth immediatly compaſſe the body of the Moone, which though it have not ſo great opacity, as to termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the ſight, yet being once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened by the Sunne, it doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt the body of the Moone under a greater forme, and hinders
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:28034:74"/> our fight from a diſtinct view of her true circumference. But of this in the next Chapter.</p>
               <p>I have now ſufficiently proved, that there are hills in the Moone, and hence it may ſeeme likely that there is alſo a world, for ſince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence hath ſome ſpeciall end in all its workes, certainly then theſe mountaines were not produced in vaine, and what more probable meaning can wee conceive there ſhould be, than to make that place convenient for habitation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="proposition">
               <head>Propoſition 10. <hi>That there is an Atmo-ſphaera, or an orbe of groſſe vaporous aire, immediately incompaſſing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Moone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS that part of our aire which is neereſt to the earth, is of a thicker ſubſtance than the other, by reaſon tis alwaies mixed with
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:28034:74"/> ſome vapours, which are continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally exhaled into it. So is it equally requiſite, that if there be a world in the Moone, that the aire about that ſhould be alike qualified with ours. Now, that there is ſuch an orbe of groſſe aire, was firſt of all (for ought I can reade) obſerved by <hi>Meſlin,</hi> afterwards aſſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by <hi>Keplar</hi> and <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide</hi> Ruſeb. Nierem. <hi>de Nat. Hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> ſince by <hi>Baptiſta Ciſatus, Sheiner</hi> with others, all of them confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it by the ſame arguments which I ſhall onely cite, and then leave this Propoſition.</p>
               <p n="1">1. 'Tis obſerved, that ſo much of the Moone as is enlightened, is alwaies part of a bigger circle then that which is darker. Their fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent experience hath proved this, and an eaſie obſervation may quickely confirme it. But now this cannot proceede from any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe ſo probable, as from this orbe of aire, eſpecially when we conſider how that planet ſhining with a borrowed light, doth not
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:28034:75"/> ſend forth any ſuch rayes as may make her appearance bigger then her body.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis obſerved in the Solary eclipſes, that there is a great trepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation about the body of the Moone, from which we may like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe argue an Atmo-ſphaera, ſince we cannot well conceive what ſo probable a cauſe there ſhould be of ſuch an appearance as this, <hi>Quod radii Solares à vaporibus Lunam ambientibus fuerint interciſi,</hi> that the Sun beames were broken and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scheiner. Roſ. Vrſ. l.</hi> 4. <hi>pars</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> refracted by the vapours that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed the Moone.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I may adde the like argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment taken from another obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which will be eaſily tried and granted. When the Sunne is eclipſed, wee diſcerne the Moone as ſhee is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> her owne naturall big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but then ſhe appeares ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what leſſe then when ſhee is in the full, though ſhe be in the ſame place of her ſuppoſed excentrick and epicycle, and therefore <hi>Tycho</hi>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:28034:75"/> hath calculated a Table for the Diameter of the divers new Moones. But now there is no reaſon ſo probable to ſalve this appearance, as to place an or be of thicker aire, neere the body of that Planet, which may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened by the reflected beames, and through which the directraies may eaſily penetrate.</p>
               <p>But ſome may object that this will not conſiſt with that which was before delivered, where I ſaid, that the thinneſt parts had leaſt light.</p>
               <p>If this were true, how comes it to paſſe then, that this aire ſhould be as bright as any of the other parts, when as tis the thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of all?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, if the light be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by reflection, then the thickeſt body hath moſt, becauſe it is beſt able to beate backe the raies, but if the light be received by illumination (eſpecially if there be an opacous body behinde,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:28034:76"/> which may double the beames by reflexion) as it is here, then I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny not but a thinne body may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine much light, and perhaps, ſome of thoſe appearances which wee take for fiery comets, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a bright cloud enlightened, ſo that probable it is, there may be ſuch aire without the Moone, and hence it comes to paſſe, that the greater ſpots are onely viſible towards her middle parts, and none neere the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, not but that there are ſome as well in thoſe parts as elſe where, but they are not there perceiveable, by reaſon of thoſe brighter vapours which hide them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="proposition">
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:28034:76"/>
               <head>Propoſition. 11. <hi>That as their world is our Moone, ſo our world is their Moone.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have already handled the firſt thing that I promiſed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Method which <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> uſes in his Booke <hi>de Mundo,</hi> and ſhew'd you the neceſſary parts that belong to this world in the Moone. In the next place 'tis requiſite that I proceed to thoſe things which are extrinſecall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, as the Seaſons, the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors, and the Inhabitants.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of the Seaſons;</p>
               <p>And if there be ſuch a world in the Moone, 'tis requiſite then that their ſeaſons ſhould be ſome way correſpondent unto ours, that they ſhould have Winter and Summer, night and day, as wee have.</p>
               <p>Now that in this Planet there is ſome ſimilitude of Winter and
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:28034:77"/> Summer is affirmed by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De gen. ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. l.</hi> 4. 12.</note> himſelfe, ſince there is one hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheare that hath alwaies heate and light, and the other that hath darkneſſe and cold. True indeed, their daies and yeeres are alwaies of one and the ſame length, but tis ſo with us alſo under the Poles, and therefore that great difference is not ſufficient to make it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unlike ours, nor can we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that every thing there ſhould be in the ſame manner as it is here below, as if nature had no way but one to bring about her pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. Wee may eaſily ſee what great differences there are amongſt us, betwixt things of the ſame <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plut. de fac. De naturâ populorum c.</hi> 3.</note> kinde. Some men (ſay they) there are, who can live onely upon ſmells, without eating any thing, and the ſame Plant, ſaith <hi>Beſoldus,</hi> hath ſometimes contrary effects. <hi>Mandragora</hi> which growes in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> inflames the luſt, wheras <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragora</hi> which grows in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces doth coole the blood &amp; q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ench luſt.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:28034:77"/>
               <p> Now if with us there be ſuch great difference betwixt things of the ſame kinde, we have no reaſon then to thinke it neceſſary that both theſe worlds ſhould be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether alike, but it may ſuffice if they bee correſpondent in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing onely, however it may be queſtioned whether it doth not ſeeme to be againſt the wiſedome of providence, to make the night of ſo great a length, when they have ſuch a long time unfit for worke? I anſwere no, ſince tis ſo, and more with us alſo under the poles; and beſides, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall length of their night is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what abated in the bigneſſe of their Moone which is our earth. For this returnes as great a light unto that Planet, as it receives from it. But for the better proofe of this, I ſhall firſt free the way from ſuch opinions as might otherwiſe hinder the ſpeede of a clearer progreſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> one of the chiefe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons <note place="margin">Plut. de fac. lunae.</note>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:28034:78"/> trons of this world in the Moone, doth directly contradict this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; affirming, that thoſe who live there may diſcerne our world as the dregges and ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all other creatures, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to them through clouds and foggy miſts, and that altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther devoid of light, being baſe and unmoveable, ſo that they might well imagine the darke place of damnation to be here ſituate, and that they onely were the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters of the world, as being in the midſt betwixt Heaven and Hell.</p>
               <p>To this I may anſwere, 'tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpake this inconſiderately, and without a reaſon, which makes him likewiſe fall into another abſurditie, when he ſayes our earth would appeare immoveable, whereas queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe though it did not, yet would it ſeeme to move, and theirs to ſtand ſtill, as the Land doth to a man in a Shippe; according to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:28034:78"/> that of the Poet:</p>
               <q>Provehimur portu, terrae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> urbeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> recedunt.</q>
               <p>And I doubt not but that inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Authour would eaſily have recanted if hee had beene but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thoſe experiences which men of latter times have found out, for the confirmation of this truth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Unto him aſſents <hi>Macrobius,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Somn. Scip. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> whoſe words are theſe; <hi>Terra ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepto ſolis lumine clareſcit, tantum-modò, non relucet.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The earth is by the Sunne-beames made bright, but not able to enlighten any thing ſo farre.</q> And his reaſon is, becauſe this being of a thicke and groſſe matter, the light is terminated in its ſuperficies, and cannot penetrate into the ſubſtance; whereas the moone doth therefore ſeeme ſo bright to us, becauſe it receives the beames within it ſelfe. But the weakneſſe of this aſſertion, may bee eaſily manifeſt by a common experience,
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:28034:79"/> for poliſhed ſteele (whoſe opacity will not give any admittance to the rayes) reflects a ſtronger heate then glaſſe, and ſo conſequently a greater light.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis the generall conſent of Philoſophers, that the reflection of the Sunne-beames from the earth doth not reach much above halfe a mile high, where they terminate the firſt region, ſo that to affirme they might aſcend to the moone, were to ſay, there were but one region of aier, which contradicts the proved and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved opinion.</p>
               <p>Unto this it may be anſwered: That it is indeed the common conſent, that the reflexion of the Sunne-beames reach onely to the ſecond region, but yet ſome there are, and thoſe too Philoſophers of good note, who thought other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ant. lect. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> Thus <hi>Plotinus</hi> is cited by <hi>Caelius, Si concipias te in ſublimi quopiam mundi loco, unde oculis ſubjiciatur terrae moles aquis cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumfuſa,</hi>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:28034:79"/> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſolis ſyderum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> radiis illuſtrata, non aliam profecto viſam iri probabile eſt, quam qualis modo viſatur lunaris globi ſpecies.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If you did conceive your ſelfe to bee in ſome ſuch high place, where you might diſcerne the whole Globe of the earth and water, when it was enlightned by the Sunnes rayes, 'tis probable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t would then appeare to you in the ſame ſhape as the moone doth now unto us.</q> Thus alſo <hi>Carolus Malapertius,</hi> whoſe <note place="margin">Praefat. ad Auſtriaca ſyd.</note> words are theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Terra haec noſtra ſi in luna conſtituti eſſemus, ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dida prorſus quaſi non ignobilis planeta, nobis appareret.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If wee were placed in the moone, and from thence beheld this our earth, it would appeare unto us very bright, like one of the nobler Planets.</q> Unto theſe doth <hi>Fronondus</hi> aſſent, when he ſayes, <hi>Credo equidem quod ſi oculus quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piam in orbe lunari foret, globum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Meteor. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Art.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>terrae &amp; aquae inſtar ingentis ſyderis</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:28034:80"/> 
                  <hi>à ſole illuſtrem conſpiceret.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">I believe that this globe of earth and water would appeare like ſome great Starre to any one, who ſhould looke upon it from the moone.</q> Now this could not be, nor could it ſhine ſo remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, unleſſe the beames of light, were reflected from it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame <hi>Fromondus</hi> expreſly holds, that the firſt region of ayre is there terminated, where the heate cauſed by reflexion begins to languiſh, whereas the beames themſelves doe paſſe a great way further. The chiefe argument which doth moſt plainely mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt this truth, is taken from a common obſervation which may be eaſily tryed.</p>
               <p>If you behold the Moone a little before or after the conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, when ſhe is in a ſextile with the Sunne, you may diſcerne not onely the part which is enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but the reſt alſo to have in it a kind of a duskiſhlight, but if you
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:28034:80"/> chuſe out ſuch a ſcituation, where ſome houſe or chimney (being ſome 70 or 80 paces diſtant from you) may hide from your eye the enlightned hornes, you may then diſcerne a greater and more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable ſhining in thoſe parts unto which the Sunne beames cannot reach; nay there is ſo great a light, that by the helpe of a good perſpective you may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne its ſpots. In ſo much that <hi>Blancanus</hi> the Jeſuite ſpeaking of it ſayes, <hi>Haec experientia ita me</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De mundi ſab. p.</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> 
                  <hi>aliquando fe fellit, ut in hunc ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorem caſu ac repente incidens, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtimarim novo quodam miraculo tempore adoleſcentis lunae factum eſſe plenilunium.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">This experiment did once ſo deceive mee, that happening upon the ſight of this brightneſſe upon a ſudden, I thought that by ſome new mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle the Moone had beene got into her full a little after her change.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But now this light is not proper
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:28034:81"/> to the Moone, it doth not proceed from the rayes of the Sunne which doth penetrate her body, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is it cauſed by any other of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and Starres. Therefore it muſt neceſſarily follow, that it comes from the earth. The two firſt of theſe I have already proved, and as for the laſt, it is confidently affirmed by <hi>Caelius, Quod ſi in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>diſquiſitionem evocet quis, an lunari ſyderi lucem foenerent planetae item alii, aſſeveranter aſtruendum non foenerare.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If any ſhould aske whether the other Planets lend any light to the Moone; I anſwer they doe not.</q> True indeed, the noble <hi>Tycho</hi> diſcuſſing the reaſon <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Progym.</hi> 1.</note> of this light attributes it to the Planet <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> and I grant that this may convey ſome light to the Moone, but that it is not the cauſe of this whereof wee now diſcourſe, is of it ſelfe ſufficiently plaine, becauſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus</hi> is ſometimes over the Moone, when as ſhee cannot convey any light to that
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:28034:81"/> part which is turned from her.</p>
               <p>It doth not proceede from the fixed ſtarres, for then it would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the ſame light in eclipſes, whereas the light at ſuch times is more ruddy and dull. Then alſo the light of the Moone would not be greater or leſſer, according to its diſtance from the edge of the earths ſhadow, ſince it did at all times equally participate this light of the ſtarres.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe there is no other body in the whole Univerſe, ſave the earth, it remaines that this light muſt neceſſarily be cauſed by that which with a juſt gratitude repaies to the Moone, ſuch il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumination as it receives from her.</p>
               <p>And as loving friends equally participate of the ſame joy and griefe, ſo doe theſe mutually par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the ſame light from the Sunne, and the ſame darkeneſſe from the eclipſes, being alſo ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally helped by one another in
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:28034:82"/> their greateſt wants: For when the Moone is in conjunction with the Sunne, and her upper part re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives all the light, then her lower Hemiſpheare (which would o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be altogether darke) is enlightened by the reflexion of the Sunne beames from the earth. When theſe two planets are in oppoſition, then that part of the earth which could not receive any light from the Sunne beames, is moſt enlightened by the Moone, being then in her full; and as ſhe doth moſt illuminate the earth when the Sunne beames cannot, ſo the gratefull earth returnes to her as great, nay greater light when ſhee moſt wants it; ſo that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies that viſible part of the Moone which receives nothing from the Sunne, is enlightened by the earth, as is proved by <hi>Galilaeus,</hi> with many more arguments, in that Treatiſe which he calls <hi>Syſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mundi.</hi> True indeed, when the Moone comes to a quartile, then
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:28034:82"/> you can neither diſcerne this light, nor yet the darker part of her body, but the reaſon is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the exuperancy of the light in the other parts. <hi>Quip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe illuſtratum medium ſpeciem</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scal. exerc.</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>recipit valentiorem,</hi> the clearer brightneſſe involves the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, it being with the ſpecies of ſight, as it is with thoſe of ſound, and as the greater noiſe drownes the leſſe, ſo the brighter object hides that which is more obſcure. But they doe alwaies in their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall viciſſitudes participate of one anothers light; ſo alſo doe they partake of the ſame defects and darknings, for when our Moone is eclipſed, then is their Sunne dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, and when our Sunne is eclipſed, then is their Moone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of its light, as you may ſee affirmed by <hi>Maeſlin. Quod ſi ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epit. Aſtro. l.</hi> 4. <hi>part.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>nobis ex alto liceret intueri, quemadmodum deficientem lunam ex longinquo ſpectare poſſumus, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deremus tempore eclipſis ſolis terrae</hi>
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:28034:83"/> 
                  <hi>aliquam partem lumine ſolis defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, eodem planè modo ſicut ex oppoſito luna deficit,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If wee might behold this globe of earth at the ſame diſtance as we doe the Moone in her defects, wee might diſcerne ſome part of it darkened in the Sunnes eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, juſt ſo as the Moone is in hers.</q> For as our Moone is eclipſed by the interpoſition of our earth, ſo is their Moone eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the interpoſition of theirs. The manner of this mutuall illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination betwixt theſe two you may plainly diſcerne in this Figure following.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:28034:83"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of Sun, Moon, and Earth</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:28034:84"/>
               <p> Where A repreſents the Sun, B the Earth, and C the Moone; Now ſuppoſe the Moone C to be in a ſextile of increaſe, when there is onely one ſmall part of her body enlightened, then the earth B will have ſuch a part of its viſible He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſpheare darkened, as is propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to that part of the Moone which is enlightened; and as for ſo much of the Moone, as the Sun beames cannot reach unto, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives light from a proportionall part of the earth which ſhines upon it, as you may plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by the Figure.</p>
               <p>You ſee then that agreement and ſimilitude which there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt our earth and the Moone. Now the greateſt difference which makes them unlike, is this, that the Moone enlightens our earth round about, whereas our earth gives light onely to that Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheare of the Moone which is viſible unto us, as may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly gathered from the conſtant
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:28034:84"/> appearance of the ſame ſpots, which could not thus come to paſſe, if the Moone had ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnall motion about its own axis, as perhaps our earth hath. And though ſome ſuppoſe her to move in an epicycle, yet this doth not ſo turne her body round, that we may diſcerne both Hemiſpheares, for according to that hypotheſis, the motion of her eccentrick, doth turne her face towards us, as much as the other doth from us.</p>
               <p>But now if any queſtion what they doe for a Moone who live in the upper part of her body? I anſwer, the ſolving of this is the moſt uncertaine and difficult thing that I know of concerning this whole matter. But yet I will give you two probable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Perhaps, the upper Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheare of the Moone doth receive a ſufficient light from thoſe planets about it, and amongſt theſe <hi>Venus</hi> (it may be) beſtowes a more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:28034:85"/> brightneſſe, ſince <hi>Galilaeus</hi> hath plainly diſcerned that ſhe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the ſame increaſes and decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the Moone hath, and 'tis probable that this may be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived there without the help of a glaſſe, becauſe they are farre neerer it than wee. When <hi>Venus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Keplar)</hi> lies downe in the Perige or lower part of her ſuppoſed Epicycle, then is ſhe in conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her husband the Sunne, from whom after ſhe hath depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the ſpace of ten moneths, ſhee gets <hi>plenum uterum,</hi> and is in the full.</p>
               <p>But you'll reply, though <hi>Venus</hi> may beſtow ſome light when ſhe is over the Moone, and in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, yet being in oppoſition, ſhe is not viſible to them, and what ſhall they then doe for light?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, then they have none: nor doth this make ſo great a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt thoſe two Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheares as there is with us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the places under the poles,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:28034:85"/> and the line, but if this bee not ſufficient, then I ſay in the ſecond place that</p>
               <p n="2">2. Perhaps there may be ſome other enligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned body above the Moone which we cannot diſcerne, nor is this altogether improbable becauſe there is almoſt the like obſerved in Saturne, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares through this glaſſe with two leſſer bodies on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ach ſide, which may ſupply the office of Moones, unto each hemiſpheare thus:</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of Saturn and Moons</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>So in this world alſo there may be ſome ſuch body, though wee cannot diſcerne it, becauſe the Moone is alwaies in a ſtreight line, betwixt our eye and that. Nor is it altogether unlikely that there ſhould bee more moones to one Orbe, becauſe <hi>Jupiter</hi> alſo is obſerved to have foure ſuch
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:28034:86"/> bodies that move round about him.</p>
               <p>But it may ſeeme a very difficult thing to conceive, how ſo groſſe and darke a body as our earth, ſhould yeeld ſuch a cleare light as proceedes from the Moone, and therefore the Cardinall <hi>de Cuſa</hi> (who thinkes every Starre to be <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De doct. ig. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> a ſeverall world) is of opinion that the light of the Sunne is not able to make them appeare ſo bright, but the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon of their ſhining is, becauſe wee behold them at a great diſtance through their regions of fire which doe ſet a ſhining luſtre upon thoſe bodies that of themſelves are darke. <hi>Vnde ſi quis eſſet extra regionem ignis, terra iſta in circumferentia ſuae regionis per medium ignis lucida ſtella appareret.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">So that if a man were beyond the region of fire, this earth would appeare through that as a bright Starre.</q> But if this were the onely reaſon then would the Moone bee
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:28034:86"/> freed from ſuch increaſes and decreaſes as ſhee is now lyable unto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Keplar</hi> thinkes that our earth receives that light whereby it ſhines from the Sunne, but this (ſaith he) is not ſuch an intended cleare brightneſſe as the Moone is capable of, and therefore hee gueſſes, that the earth there is of a more chokie ſoyle like the Ile of <hi>Creete,</hi> and ſo is better able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect a ſtronger light, whereas our earth muſt ſupply this inten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion with the quantity of its body, but this I conceive to be a needleſſe conjecture, ſince our earth if all things were well conſidered will be ſound able enough to reflect as great a light. For</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider its opacity, if you marke theſe ſublunary things, you ſhall perceive that amongſt them, thoſe that are moſt perſpicuous, are not ſo well able to reverberate the Sunne beames as the thicker bodies. The rayes paſſe ſingly
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:28034:87"/> through a diaphanous matter, but in an opacous ſubſtance they are doubled in their returne and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed by reflexion. Now if the moone and the other Planets can ſhine ſo clearely by beating backe the Sunne beames, why may not the earth alſo ſhine as well, which agrees with them in the cauſe of this brightneſſe their opacity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider what a cleare light wee may diſcerne refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted from the earth in the middeſt of Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and withall conceive how much greater that muſt bee which is under the line, where the rayes are more directly and ſtrongly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberated.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider the great diſtance at which wee behold the Planets, for this muſt needs adde much to their ſhining and therefore <hi>Cuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> (in the above cited place) thinkes that if a man were in the Sunne, that Planet would not appeare ſo bright to him, as now
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:28034:87"/> it doth to us, becauſe then his eye could diſcerne but little, whereas here wee may comprehend the beames as they are contracted in a narrow body. <hi>Keplar</hi> beholding the earth from a high mountaine when it was enlightned by the Sunne confeſſes that it appeared unto him of an incredible bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, whereas then the refl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cted rayes entered into his ſight ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely; but how much brighter would it have appeared if hee might in a direct line behold the whole globe of earth and theſe rayes gathered together. So that if wee conſider that great light which the earth receives from the Sunne in the Summer, and then ſuppoſe wee were in the Moone, where wee might ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the whole earth hanging in thoſe vaſt ſpaces where there is nothing to termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate the ſight, but thoſe beames which are there contracted into a little compaſſe; I ſay, if wee doe well conſider this, wee may eaſily
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:28034:88"/> conceive, that our earth appeares as bright to thoſe other inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in the Moone, as theirs doth to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="proposition">
               <head>Propoſition 12. <hi>That tis probable there may bee ſuch Meteors belonging to that world in the Moone, as there are with us.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PLutarch</hi> diſcuſſing this point affirmes that it is not neceſſary there ſhould be the ſame meanes of growth and fructifying in both theſe worlds, ſince nature might in her policy finde out more waies then one how to bring about the ſame effect. But however he thinks it is probable that the Moone her ſelfe ſendeth forth warme winds, and by the ſwiftneſſe of her moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there ſhould breathe out a ſweet and comfortable ayer, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant dewes and gentle moyſture,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:28034:88"/> which might ſerve for the refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and nouriſhment of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants and plants in that other world.</p>
               <p>But ſince they have all things alike with us, as ſea and land, and vaporous ayer encompaſſing both, I ſhould rather therefore thinke that nature there ſhould uſe the ſame way of producing meteors as ſhe doth with us (and not by a motion as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſuppoſes) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhee doth not love to vary from her uſuall operations with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome extraordinary impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but ſtill keepes her beaten path unleſſe ſhe be driven thence.</p>
               <p>One argument whereby I ſhall manifeſt this truth, may be taken from thoſe new Starres which have appeared in divers ages of the world, and by their paralax have beene diſcerned to have been above the Moone, ſuch as was that in <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> that in <hi>Sagitta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> with many others betwixt the Planets. <hi>Hipparchus</hi> in his time
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:28034:89"/> tooke eſpeciall notice of ſuch as <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. nat. hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 26</note> theſe, and therefore fancied out ſuch conſtellations in which to place the Starres, ſhewing how many there were in every aſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me, that ſo afterwards poſterity might know, whether there were any new Starre produced or any old one miſſing. Now the nature of theſe Comets may probably manifeſt, that in this other world there are other meteors alſo; for theſe in all likelihood are nothing e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e but ſuch evaporations cauſed by the Sunne, from the bodies of the Planets. I ſhall prove this by ſhewing the improbabilities and inconveniences of any other opinion.</p>
               <p>For the better purſuite of this 'tis in the firſt place requiſite that I deale with our chiefe adverſary, <hi>Caeſar la Galla,</hi> who doth moſt directly oppoſe that truth which is here to bee proved. Hee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to confirme the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptibility of the Heavens,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:28034:89"/> and being there to ſatisfie the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which is taken from theſe comets, He anſwers it thus: <hi>Aut argumentum deſumptum ex para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laxi non eſt efficax, aut ſi eſt efficax, eorum inſtrumentorum uſum deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere, vel ratione aſtri vel medii, vel diſtantiae, aut ergo erat in ſuprema parte aeris, aut ſi in coelo, tum for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan factum erat ex reflectione radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum Saturni &amp; Jovis, qui tunc in conjunctione fuerant.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Either the argument from the paralax is not eſſicacious, or if it be, yet the uſe of the inſtruments might deceive either in regard of the ſtarre or the <hi>medium,</hi> or the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and ſo this comet might be in the upper regions of the aire, or if it were in the heavens, there it might be produced by the reflexion of the rayes from <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> who were then in conjunction.</q> You ſee what ſhifts hee is driven to, how he runnes up and downe to many ſtarting holes, that hee may find
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:28034:90"/> ſome ſhelter, and in ſtead of the ſtrength of reaſon, he anſwers with a multitude of words, thinking (as the Proverbe is) that hee may uſe haile, when hee hath no thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Nihilturpius</hi> (ſaith <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 95.</note> 
                  <hi>Seneca) dubio eſt incerto, pedem modo refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rente, modo producente.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">What can there bee more unſeemely in one that ſhould be a faire diſputant, then to be now here, now there, and ſo uncertaine, that one cannot tell where to find him.</q> He thinkes that there are not Comets in the heavens, becauſe there may be many other reaſons of ſuch appearances, but what he knowes not, perhaps (he ſaies) that argument from the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralax is not ſufficient, or if it be, then there may be ſome deceit in the obſervation. To this I may ſafely ſay, that hee may juſtly be accounted a weake Mathematici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an who miſtruſts the ſtrength of this argument, nor can hee know much in Aſtronomy, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:28034:90"/> not the paralax, which is the foundation of that Science, and I am ſure that hee is a timerous man, who dares not believe the frequent experience of his ſenſes, or truſt to a demonſtration.</p>
               <p>True indeed, I grant tis poſſible, that the eye, the <hi>medium,</hi> and the diſtance may al deceive the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, but I would have him ſhew which of all theſe was likely to cauſe an error in this obſervation? Meerely to ſay they might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived is no ſufficient anſwer, for by this I might confute the poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of all Aſtronomers, and affirme the ſtarres are hard by us, becauſe 'tis poſſible they may be deceived in their obſerving that diſtance. But I forbeare any further reply; my opinion is of that Treatiſe, that either it was ſet forth purpoſely to tempt a confutation, that hee might ſee the opinion of <hi>Galilaeus</hi> confirmed by others, or elſe it was invented with as much haſte and negligence as it was printed, there
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:28034:91"/> being in it almoſt as many faults as lines.</p>
               <p>Others thinke that theſe are not any new Comets, but ſome ancient ſtarres that were there before, which now ſhine with that unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all brightneſſe, by reaſon of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſition of ſuch vapors which doe multiply their light, and ſo the alteration will be here onely, and not in the heavens. Thus <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> thought the appearance of the milkie way was produced, for he held that there were many little ſtarres, which by their influence did conſtantly attract ſuch a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pour towards that place of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo that it alwaies appeared white. Now by the ſame reaſon may a brighter vapor be the cauſe of theſe appearances.</p>
               <p>But how probable ſoever this opinion may ſeeme, yet if well conſidered, you ſhall finde it to be altogether abſurd and impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Theſe ſtarres were never
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:28034:91"/> ſeene there before, and tis not like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that a vapour being hard by us can ſo multiply that light which could not before be at all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned.</p>
               <p n="2">2. This ſuppoſed vapour can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be either contracted into a narrow compaſſe or dilated into a broad: 1. it could not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a little ſpace, for then that ſtarre would not appeare with the ſame multiplied light to thoſe in other climates: 2. it cannot be a dilated vapour, for then other ſtarres which were diſcerned through the ſame vapour would ſeeme as bigg as that; this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the ſame in effect with that of the paralax, as you may ſee in this Figure.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:28034:92"/>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>diagram of a hemisphere of Earth, the atmosphere, and space</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>Suppoſe A B to be a Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpheare of one earth, C D to be the upper part of the higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, in which there might be either a contracted vapour, as G, or elſe a dilated one, as H I. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe E F likewiſe to repreſent halfe the heavens, wherein was this appearing Comet at K. Now I ſay, that a contracted vapour, as G could not cauſe this appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, becauſe an inhabitant at M could not diſcerne the ſame ſtarre
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:28034:92"/> with this brightneſſe, but perhaps another at L, betwixt which the vapour is directly interpoſed. Nor could it be cauſed by a dilated vapour, as H I, becauſe then all the ſtarres that were diſcerned through it would be perceived with the ſame brightneſſe.</p>
               <p>Tis neceſſary therefore that the cauſe of this appearance ſhould be in the heavens. And this is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the moſt and beſt Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers. But, ſay ſome, this doth not argue any naturall alteration in thoſe purer bodies, ſince tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that the concourſe of many little vagabond ſtarres by the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their beames may cauſe ſo great a light. Of this opinion were <hi>Anaxagor as</hi> and <hi>Zeno</hi> amongſt the ancient, and <hi>Baptiſta Ciſatus, Blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus,</hi> with others amongſt our moderne Aſtronomers. For, ſay they, when there happens to be a concourſe of ſome few ſtarres, then doe many other flie unto them from all the parts of heaven
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:28034:93"/> like ſo many Bees unto their King. But 1. tis not likely that amongſt thoſe which wee count the fixed ſtarres there ſhould be any ſuch uncertaine motions, that they can wander from all parts of the heavens, as if Nature had neglected them, or forgot to appoint them a determinate courſe. 2. If there be ſuch a conflux of theſe, as of Bees to their King, then what reaſon is there that they doe not ſtill tarry with it, that ſo the Comet may not he diſſolved? But enough of this. You may commonly ſee it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed by many other arguments. Others there are, who affirme theſe to be ſome new created ſtars, produced by an extraordinary ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall power. I anſwer, true indeed, tis poſſible they might be ſo, but however tis not likely they were ſo, ſince ſuch appearances may be ſalved ſome other way, wherefore to fly unto a miracle for ſuch things, were a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to nature, and to derogate
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:28034:93"/> from her skill, an indignity much miſ-becomming a man who profeſſes himſelfe to bee a Philoſopher. <hi>Miraculum</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>eſt ignorantiae Aſylum,</hi> a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle often ſerves for the recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle of a lazy ignorance which any induſtrious Spirit would be aſhamed of, it being but an idle way to ſhift off the labour of any further ſearch. But her's the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of it, we firſt tye our ſelves unto <hi>Ariſtotle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> principles, and then conclude that nothing could contradict them but a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, whereas 'twould be much better for the Common-wealth of learning, if we would ground our principles rather upon the frequent experiences of our owne, then the bare authority of others.</p>
               <p>Some there are who thinke, that theſe Comets are nothing elſe, but exhalations from our earth, carryed up into the higher parts of the Heaven. So <hi>Pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:28034:94"/> 
                  <hi>Rothmannus &amp; Galilaeus,</hi> but this <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tycho Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gym. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> is not poſſible, ſince by compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation 'tis found that one of them is above 300 times bigger than the whole Globe of Land and Water. Others therefore have thought that they did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from the body of the Sun, and that that Planet onely is <hi>Cometarum officina, unde tanquam emiſſarii &amp; exploratores emitteren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, brevi ad ſolem redituri:</hi> The ſhop or forge of Comets from whence they were ſent, like ſo many ſpies, that they might in ſome ſhort ſpace returne againe, but this cannot be, ſince if ſo much matter had proceeded from him alone, it would have made a ſenſible diminution in his body. The Noble <hi>Tycho</hi> therefore thinkes that they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of ſome ſuch fluider parts of the Heaven, as the milky way is framed of, which being condenſt together, yet not attaining to the conſiſtency of a Starre, is in
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:28034:94"/> ſome ſpace of time rarifyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into its wonted nature. But this is not likely, for if there had beene ſo great a condenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as to make them ſhine ſo bright and laſt ſo long, they would then ſenſibly have moved downewards towards ſome cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of gravity, becauſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is condenſt muſt neceſſarily grow heavier, whereas theſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeemed to aſcend higher, as they laſted longer. But ſome may object, that a thing may be of the ſame weight, when it is rarified, as it had while it was condenſt, ſo metals when they are melted and when they are cold, ſo water alſo when it is frozen, and when it is fluid, doth not differ in reſpect of gravity. But to theſe I anſwere: Firſt, Metals are not rarified by mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, but molified. Secondly, waters are not properly conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but congealed into a harder ſubſtance, the parts being not
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:28034:95"/> contracted cloſer together, but ſtill poſſeſſing the ſame exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <p>And beſide, what likely cauſe can we conceive of this conden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, unleſſe there be ſuch qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities there, as there are in our ayer, and then why may not the Planets have the like qualities as our earth? and if ſo, then 'tis more probable that they are made by the ordinary way of nature, as they are with us, and conſiſt of exhalations from the bodies of the Planets. Nor is this a ſingular opinion; but it ſeemed moſt likely to <hi>Camillus</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Comet. l.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>Apolog. Meteor. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Glorioſus. Th. Campanella, Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondus,</hi> with ſome others. But if you aske whither all theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations ſhall returne, I anſwer every one into his owne Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net: if it be againe objected, that <note place="margin">Iohan. Fabr. Carolus Malaptius de Heliocyc. Scheiner. Roſa Viſina.</note> then there will be ſo many cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of gravity, and each ſeverall Planet will be a diſtinct world; I reply, perhaps all of them are
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:28034:95"/> ſo except the Sunne, though <hi>Cuſanus</hi> thinks there is one alſo, and later times have diſcovered ſome leſſer Planets moving round about him. But as for <hi>Saturne,</hi> he hath two Moones on each ſide. <hi>Jupiter</hi> hath foure, that incircle his body with their motion. <hi>Venus</hi> is obſerved to increaſe and decreaſe as the Moone. <hi>Mars,</hi> and all the reſt, derive their light from the Sunne onely. Concerning <hi>Mercury,</hi> there hath beene little or no ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, becauſe for the moſt part, he lies hid under the Sunne beames, and ſeldome appeares by himſelfe. So that if you conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their quantity, their opacity, or theſe other diſcoveries, you ſhall finde it probable enough, that each of them may be a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall world. But this would bee too much for to vent at the firſt: the chiefe thing at which I now ayme in this diſcourſe, is to
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:28034:96"/> prove that there may bee one in the Moone.</p>
               <p>It hath beene before confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that there was a ſpheare of thicke vaporous ayer encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Moone, as the firſt and ſecond regions doe this earth. I have now ſhewed, that thence ſuch exhalations may proceed as do produce the Comets: now from hence it may probably follow, that there may be winde alſo and raine, with ſuch other meteors as are common amongſt us. This conſequence is ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant, that <hi>Fromondus</hi> dares <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De meteor. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Art.</hi> 6.</note> not deny it, though hee would (as he confeſſes himſelfe) for it the Sunne be able to exhale from them ſuch fumes as may cauſe Comets, why not then ſuch as may cauſe windes, and why not ſuch alſo as may cauſe raine, ſince I have above ſhewed, that there is Sea and Land as with us. Now raine ſeemes to bee more eſpecially requiſite for them,
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:28034:96"/> ſince it may allay the heate and ſcorchings of the Sunne, when he is over their heads. And na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath thus provided for thoſe in <hi>Peru,</hi> with the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants under the line.</p>
               <p>But if there be ſuch great, and frequent alterations in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, why cannot we diſcerne them?</p>
               <p>I anſwere:</p>
               <p n="1">1. There may be ſuch, and we not able to perceive them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the weakenes of our eye, and the diſtance of thoſe places from us, they are the words of <hi>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus,</hi> as they are quoted by <hi>Fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondus</hi> in the above cited place) <hi>Poſſunt maximae permutationes in coelo fieri, etiam ſi a nobis non conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rantur, hoc viſus noſtri debilita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; immenſa coeli diſtantia faciunt.</hi> And unto him aſſents <hi>Fromondus</hi> himſelfe, when a little after hee ſaies, <hi>Si in ſphaeris planetarum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, plurima forſan coeleſtium nebularum vellera toto athere paſſim</hi>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:28034:97"/> 
                  <hi>diſperſa videremus, quorum ſpecies jam evaneſcit nimia ſpatis inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capedine.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">If we did live in the ſpheares of the Planets, wee might there perhaps diſcerne many great clouds diſperſed through the whole Heavens, which are not now viſible by reaſon of this great diſtance.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Maeſlin</hi> and <hi>Keplaer</hi> affirme, that they have ſeene ſome of theſe alterations. The words of <hi>Maeſlin</hi> are theſe (as I finde them <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Diſſert.</hi> 2. <hi>cum nunc. Galil.</hi>
                  </note> cited.) <hi>In eclipſi lunari veſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re Dominicae Palmarum A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ni</hi> 1605. <hi>in corpore lunae verſus Boream, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gricans quaedam macula conſpecta fuit, obſcurior caetero toto corpore, quod candentis ferri figuram repreae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentabat; dixiſſes nubila in multam regionem extenſa pluviis &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuoſis imbribus gravida, cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi ab excelſorum montium jugis in humiliora convallium loca vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere non rarò contingit.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">In that lunary eclipſe which happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the even of Palme-ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:28034:97"/> in the yeere 1605 there was a certaine blackiſh ſpot diſcerned in the Northerly part of the Moone, being dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker than any other place of her body, and repreſenting the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of red hot iron; you might conjecture that it was ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated cloud, being pregnant with ſhowers, for thus do ſuch lower clouds appeare from the tops of high mountaines.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Vnto this I may ad another teſtimony of <hi>Bapt. Ciſatus,</hi> as he is quoted by <hi>Nicrembergius,</hi> groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiſt. Nat. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> upon an obſervation taken 23. yeeres after this of <hi>Maeſlin,</hi> and writ to this <hi>Euſeb. Nicrem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg.</hi> in a letter by that diligent and judicious Aſtronomer. The words of it runne thus: <hi>Et qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem in eclipſi nupra ſolari quae fuit ipſo die natali Chriſti, obſervavi clare in luna ſoli ſuppoſita, quidpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quod valde probat id ipſum quod Cometae quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; maculae ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares urgent, nempe coelum non eſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="184" facs="tcp:28034:98"/> 
                  <hi>a tennitate &amp; variationibus aeris exemptum, nam circa lunam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verti eſſe ſphaeram ſeu orbem quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam vap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roſum, non ſecus at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum terram, adeo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſicut ex terra in aliquam uſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpharam vapores &amp; exhalationes expirant, ita quo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex luna.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">In that late ſolary eclipſe which happened on Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas day, when the Moone was juſt under the Sunne, I plainly diſcerned that in her which may clearely confirme what the Comets and Sunnes ſpots doe ſeeme to prove, <hi>viz.</hi> that the heavens are not ſolid, nor freed from thoſe changes which our aire is liable unto, for about the Moone I percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch an orbe, of vaporous aire, as that is which doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſe our earth, and as va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours and exhalations are rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from our earth into this aire, ſo are they alſo from the Moone.</q>
               </p>
               <p>You ſee what probable
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:28034:98"/> grounds and plaine teſtimonies I have brought for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of this Propoſition: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other things in this behalfe might be ſpoken, which for brevity ſake I now omit, and paſſe uno the next.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="proposition">
               <head>Propoſition 13. <hi>That tis probable there may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hubitants in this other World, but of what kinde they are is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Have already handled the Seaſons and Meteors belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this new World: tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that in the next place I ſhould come unto the third thing which I promiſed, and to ſay ſomewhat of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, concerning whom there might be many difficult queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons raiſed, as whether that place be more inconvenient for habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:28034:99"/> then our World (as <hi>Keplar</hi> thinkes) whether they are the ſeed of <hi>Adam,</hi> whether they are there in a bleſſed eſtate, or elſe what meanes there may be for their ſalvation, with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch uncertaine enquiries, which I ſhall willingly omit, leaving it to their examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have more leiſure and learning for the ſearch of ſuch particulars.</p>
               <p>Being for mine own part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent only to ſetdowne ſuch notes belonging unto theſe which I have obſerved in other Writers. <hi>Cum tota illa regio nobis ignota ſit, remanent inhabitatores illi ignoti</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De doct. ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantia. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>penitus,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cuſanus)</hi> ſince we know not the regions of that place, wee muſt be altogether ignorant of the inhabitants. There hath not yet beene any ſuch diſcovery concerning theſe, upon which wee may build a certainty, or good probability: well may we gueſſe at them, and
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:28034:99"/> that too very doubtfully, but we can know nothing, for if we doe hardly gueſſe aright at things which be upon earth, if with labour we doe finde the things <note place="margin">Wiſd. 9. 16.</note> that are at hand, how then can we ſearch out theſe things that are in heaven? What a little is that which we know, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of thoſe many matters contained within this great Vniverſe, this whole globe of earth and water? though it ſeeme to us to be of a large ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, yet it beares not ſo great a proportion unto the whole frame of Nature, as a ſmall ſand doth unto it, and what can ſuch little creatures as we diſcerne, who are tied to this point of earth? or what can they in the Moone know of us? If wee underſtand any thing (ſaith <hi>Eſdras)</hi> tis nothing but <note place="margin">2 Eſd. 4. 21</note> that which is upon the earth, and he that dwelleth above in the heavens, may onely under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:28034:100"/> the things that are above in the height of the heavens.</p>
               <p>So that 'twere a very neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thing for us to ſearch after any particulars, however we may gueſſe in the generall that there are ſome inhabitants in that Planet: for why elſe did providence furniſh that place with all ſuch conveniences of habitation as have beene above declared?</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, perhaps, is there not too great and intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable a heate, ſince the Sunne is in their Zenith every moneth, and doth tarry there ſo long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he leaves it?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, 1. This may, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, be remedied (as it is under the line) by the frequency of mid-day ſhowers, which may cloud their Sunne, and coole their earth: 2. The equality of their nights doth much temper the ſcorching of the day, and the extreme cold that comes
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:28034:100"/> from the one, require ſome ſpace before it can be diſpelled by the other, ſo that the heate ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a great while before it can have the victory, hath not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards much time to rage in. Wherfore notwithſtanding this, yet that place may remaine ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable. And this was the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the <hi>Cardinal de Cuſa,</hi> when ſpeaking of this Planet, he ſaies, <hi>Hic locus Mundi eſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatio</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De doct. ign. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 12.</note> 
                  <hi>hominum &amp; animalium at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vegetabilium.</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">This part of the world is inhabited by men and beaſts and plants.</q> To him aſſented <hi>Campanella,</hi> but he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not determine whether there were men or rather ſome other kinde of creatures. If they were men, then he thinks they could not be infected with <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne; yet perhaps, they had ſome of their owne, which might make them liable to the ſame miſery with us, out of which, perhaps, they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:28034:101"/> by the ſame means as we, the death of Chriſt, and thus he thinks that place of the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> may be interpreted, where the Apoſtle ſaies, <hi>God gathered all</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>things together in Chriſt, both which are in earth, and which are in the heavens:</hi> So alſo that of the ſame Apoſtle to the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi> where hee ſaies, that <hi>it pleaſed the Father to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>all things unto himſelfe by Chriſt, whether they be things in earth, or things in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I dare not jeſt with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truths, or apply theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces according as fancy directs. As I thinke this opinion doth not any where contradict Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo I thinke likewiſe, that it cannot be proved from it, wherefore <hi>Campanella's</hi> ſecond conjecture may be more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, that the inhabitants of that world, are not men as we are, but ſome other kinde of creatures which beare ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:28034:101"/> and likeneſſe to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and <hi>Cuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus</hi> too thinks they differ from us in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects; I will ſet downe his words as they may be found in the above cited place, <hi>Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus in regione ſolis magis eſſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares, claros &amp; illuminatos intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuares habitatores, ſpiritualiores etiam quam in luna, ubi magis lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natici, &amp; in terra, magis materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ales, &amp; groſſi, ut illi intellectualis naturae ſolares ſint multum in actu &amp; parum in potentia; terreni vero magis in potentia, &amp; parum in actu, lunares in medio fluctuantes. Hoc quidem opinamur ex influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ignili ſolis aqua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ica ſimul &amp; aeria lunae, &amp; gravedine materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ali terrae, &amp; conſimiliter de aliis ſtellarum regionibus ſuſpicantes, nullam habitatoribus carêre, quaſi tot ſint partes particulares mundiales unius univerſi, quot ſunt ſtellae quarum non eſt numerus, niſi apud eum qui omnia in numero creavit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:28034:102"/>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">We may conjecture (ſaith he) the inhabiters of the Sunne are like to the nature of that Planet, more cleare and bright, more intellectuall and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall than thoſe in the Moone where they are neerer to the nature of that duller Planet, and thoſe of the earth being more groſſe and materiall than either, ſo that theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectuall natures in the Sun, are more forme than matter, thoſe in the earth more mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than forme, and thoſe in the Moone betwixt both. This we may gueſſe from the fierie influence of the Sunne, the watery and aereous influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Moone, as alſo the materiall heavineſſe of the earth. In ſome ſuch manner likewiſe is it with the regions of the other ſtarres, for wee conjecture that none of them are without inhabitants, but that there are ſo many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:28034:102"/> worlds and parts of this one univerſe, as there are ſtars which are innumerable, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be to him who created all things in number.</q>
               </p>
               <p>For he held that the ſtars were not all in one equall orbe as wee commonly ſuppoſe, but that ſome were farre higher than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers which made them appeare leſſe, and that many others were ſo farre above any of theſe, that they were altogether inviſible unto us. An opinion (which as I conceive) hath not any great probability for it, nor certainty againſt it.</p>
               <p>The Prieſt of <hi>Saturne</hi> relating to <hi>Pluiarch</hi> (as he faignes it) the nature of theſe Selenites, told him they were of divers diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, ſome deſiring to live in the lower parts of the Moone, where they might looke downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon us, while others were more ſurely mounted aloft, all of them ſhining like the rayes of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:28034:103"/> the Sunne, and as being victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious are crowned with gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands made with the wings of <hi>Euſtathia</hi> or <hi>Conſtancie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath beene the opinion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſome of the Ancients, that their heavens and Elyſian fields were in the Moone where the aire is moſt quiet and pure. Thus <hi>Socrates,</hi> thus <hi>Plato,</hi> with his followers, did eſteeme this to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. Com. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> be the place where thoſe purer ſoules inhabite, who are freed from the Sepulchre, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion of the body. And by the Fable of <hi>Ceres,</hi> continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wandring in ſearch of her daughter <hi>Proſerpina,</hi> is meant no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but the longing deſire of men, who live upon <hi>Ceres</hi> earth, to attaine a place in <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerpina,</hi> the Moone or heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plutarch</hi> alſo ſeemes to aſſent unto this, but he thinkes more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that there are two places of happineſſe anſwerable to thoſe two parts which he fancies to
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:28034:103"/> remaine of a man when hee is dead, the ſoule and the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; the ſoule he thinkes is made of the Moone, and as our bodies doe ſo proceede from the duſt of this earth, that they ſhall returne to it hereafter, ſo our ſoules were generated out of that Planet, and ſhall be reſolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it againe, whereas the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſhall aſcend unto the Sun, out of which it was made, where it ſhall poſſeſſe an eternity of well being, and farre greater happineſſe than that which is enjoyed in the Moone. So that when a man dies, if his ſoule be much polluted, then muſt it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and downe in the middle regions of the aire where hell is, and there ſuffer unſpeakbale tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for thoſe ſinnes whereof it is guilty. Whereas the ſoules of better men, when they have in ſome ſpace of time beene pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from that impurity which they did derive from the body,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:28034:104"/> then doe they returne into the Moone, where they are poſſeſt with ſuch a joy, as thoſe men feele who profeſſe holy myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, from which place (ſaith he) ſome are ſent downe to have the ſuperintendance of oracles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diligent either in the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the good, either from or in all perills, and the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or puniſhment of all wicked actions, but if in theſe imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they miſ-behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, then are they againe to be impriſoned in a body, otherwiſe they remaine in the Moone till their body be reſolved into it, and the underſtanding being cleared from all impediments, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends to the Sun which is its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per place. But this requires a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe ſpace of time, according to the divers affections of the ſoule. As for thoſe who have beene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired and honeſt, addicting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a ſtudious and quiet life, theſe are quickly preferred to a
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:28034:104"/> higher happineſſe. But as for ſuch who have buſied themſelves in many broyles, or have beene vehement in the proſecution of any luſt, as the ambitious, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous, the wrathfull man, theſe ſtill retaine the glimpſes and dreames of ſuch things as they have performed in their bodies, which makes them either altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unfit to remaine there where they are, or elſe keepes them long ere they can put off their ſoules. Thus you ſee <hi>Plutarchs</hi> opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning the inhabitants and neighbours of the Moone, which (according to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Academickes) hee delivers in a third perſon; you ſee he makes that Planet an infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour kind of heaven, and though he differ in many circumſtances, yet doth hee deſcribe it to be ſome ſuch place, as wee ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Paradiſe to be. You ſee likewiſe his opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the place of damned ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:28034:105"/> that it is in the middle regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the aire, and in neither of theſe is hee ſingular, but ſome more late and Orthodox Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have agreed with him. As for the place of hell, many think it may be in the aire, as well as any where elſe.</p>
               <p>True indeede, S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auſtin</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Civit. Dei. l.</hi> 22. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> that this place cannot be diſcovered; But others there are who can ſhew the ſituation of it out of Scripture; Some holding it to be in ſome other world without this, becauſe our Saviour calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 30.</note> darkeneſſe. But the moſt will have it placed towards the center of our earth, becauſe 'tis <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 9.</note> ſaid, Chriſt deſcended into the lower parts of the earth, and ſome of theſe are ſo confident, that this is its ſituation, that they can deſcribe you its bigneſſe alſo, and of what capacity it is. <hi>Francis Ribera</hi> in his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment on the <hi>Revelations,</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:28034:105"/> words, where tis ſaid, that the blood went out of the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, <note place="margin">Rev. 14. 20</note> even unto the horſes bridles by the ſpace of one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and ſixe hundred furlongs, interprets them to be meant of hell, and that that number ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes the diameter of its conca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, which is 200 <hi>Italian</hi> miles; but <hi>Leſſius</hi> thinkes that this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Morib. div. l.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> gives them too much roome in hell, and therefore he gueſſes that 'tis not ſo wide; for (ſaith hee) the diameter of one league being cubically multiplyed, will make a ſpheare capable of 800000 millions of damned bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, allowing to each ſixe foot in the ſquare, whereas (ſaies he) tis certaine that there ſhall not be one hundred thouſand milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in all that ſhall be damned. You ſee the bold <hi>Ieſuit</hi> was care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that every one ſhould have but roome enough in hell, and by the ſtrangeneſſe of the conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, you may gueſſe that he had
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:28034:106"/> rather be abſurd, than ſeeme ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uncharitable or ignorant. I remember there is a relation in <hi>Pliny,</hi> how that <hi>Dionyſiodorus</hi> a Mathematician, being dead, did ſend a letter from this place to ſome of his friends upon earth, to certifie them what diſtance there was betwixt the center and ſuperficies: hee might have done well to have prevented this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, and enformed them the utmoſt capacity of that place. However, certaine it is, that that number cannot be knowne, and probable it is, that the place is not yet determined, but that hell is there where there is any tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented ſoule, which may be in the regions of the aire as well as in the center; but of this onely occaſionally, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Plutarchs</hi> opinion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe that are round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Moone; as for the Moone it ſelfe, hee eſteemes it to be a lower kind of heaven, and
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:28034:106"/> therefore in another place hee <note place="margin">Curſilent oracula.</note> calls it a terreſtriall ſtarre, and an Olympian or celeſtiall earth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable, as I conceive, to the paradiſe of the Schoolemen, and that paradiſe was either in or neere the Moone, is the opinion of ſome later Writers, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived it (in all likelihood) from the aſſertion of <hi>Plato,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, this of <hi>Plutarch. Toſtatus</hi> laies this opinion upon <hi>Iſiodor.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Sr. <hi>W. Raw. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. § 7. <hi>in Gen.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Hiſpalenſis,</hi> and the venerable <hi>Bede;</hi> and <hi>Pererius</hi> fathers it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Strabus</hi> and <hi>Rabanus</hi> his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Some would have it to be ſituated in ſuch a place as could not be diſcovered, which cauſed the penman of <hi>Eſdras</hi> to make it a harder matter to know the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goings of Paradiſe, then to weigh the weight of the fire, or meaſure the blaſts of wind, or call againe a day that is paſt. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <note place="margin">2 Eſd. 4. 7.</note> this, there be ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who thinke that it is on the top of ſome high mountaine un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:28034:107"/> the line, and theſe interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the torrid Zone to be the fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſword whereby Paradiſe was guarded. 'Tis the conſent of divers others, who agree in this, that Paradiſe is ſituated in ſome high and eminent place. So <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatus:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">In Geneſ.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſt etiam Paradiſus ſitu al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſima, ſupra omnem terrae altitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Paradiſe is ſituated in ſome high place above the earth:</q> and therefore in his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment upon the 49. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> he underſtands the bleſſing of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> concerning the everlaſting hills to be meant of Paradiſe, and the bleſſing it ſelfe to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a promiſe of Chriſts comming, by whoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion the gates of Paradiſe ſhould be opened. Vnto him aſſented <hi>Rupertus, Scotus,</hi> and moſt of the other Schoolemen, as I find them <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Comment. in</hi> 2 <hi>Gen. v.</hi> 8. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. § 6. 7.</note> cited by <hi>Pererius,</hi> and out of him in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>W. Rawleigh.</hi> Their reaſon was this: becauſe in probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty this place was not overflowed
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:28034:107"/> by the flood, ſince there were no ſinners there which might draw that curſe upon it. Nay <hi>Toſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> thinkes that the body of <hi>Enoch</hi> was kept there, and ſome of the Fathers, as <hi>Tertullion</hi> and <hi>Auſtin</hi> have affirmed, that the bleſſed ſoules were reſerved in that place till the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therefore 'tis likely that it was not overflowed by the flood; and beſides, ſince all men ſhould have went naked if <hi>Adam</hi> had not fell, 'tis requiſite therefore that it ſhould be ſitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in ſome ſuch place where it might be priviledged from the extremities of heat and cold. But now this could not be (they (thought) ſo conveniently in any lower, as it might in ſome higher aire. For theſe and ſuch like conſiderations have ſo many affirmed that Paradiſe was in a high elevated place, which ſome have conceived could be no where but in the Moone: For
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:28034:108"/> it could not be in the top of any mountaine, nor can we thinke of any other body ſeparated from this earth which can be a more convenient place for habitation than this Planet, therefore they concluded that it was there.</p>
               <p>It could not be on the top of any mountaine.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe wee have expreſſe <note place="margin">Gen. 7. 19.</note> Scripture, that the higheſt of them was overflowed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe it muſt be of a greater extenſion, and not ſome ſmall patch of ground, ſince tis likely all men ſhould have lived there, if <hi>Adam</hi> had not fell. But for a ſatisfaction of theſe argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, together with a farther diſcourſe of Paradiſe, I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre you to thoſe who have written purpoſely upon this ſubject. Being content for my owne part to have ſpoken ſo much of it, as may conduce to ſhew the opinion of others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the inhabitants of the
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:28034:108"/> Moone, I dare not my ſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme any thing of theſe Sele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites, becauſe I know not any ground whereon to build any probable opinion. But I thinke that future ages will diſcover more; and our poſterity, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, may invent ſome meanes for our better acquaintance with theſe inhabitants. Tis the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of providence not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſhew us all, but to lead us a long from the knowledge of one thing to another. 'Twas a great while ere the Planets were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the fixed ſtars, and ſome time after that ere the morning and evening ſtarre were found to be the ſame, and in greater ſpace I doubt not but this alſo, and farre greater myſteries will be diſcovered. In the firſt ages of the world the Iſlanders either thought themſelves to be the onely dwellers upon the earth, or elſe if there were any other, yet they could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:28034:109"/> conceive how they might have any commerce with them, being ſevered by the deepe and broad ſea, but the aftertimes found out the invention of ſhips, in which notwithſtanding none but ſome bold daring men durſt venture, there being few ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute as to commit themſelves unto the vaſt Ocean, and yet now how eaſie a thing is this, even to a timorous and cowardly nature? So, perhaps, there may be ſome other meanes invented for a conveyance to the Moone, and though it may ſeeme a terrible and impoſſible thing ever to paſſe through the vaſt ſpaces of the aire, yet no queſtion there would be ſome men who durſt venture this as well as the other. True indeed, I cannot conceive any poſſible meanes for the like diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of this conjecture, ſince there can be no ſailing to the Moone, unleſſe that were true which the Poets doe but feigne,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:28034:109"/> that ſhee made her bed in the Sea. Wee have not now any <hi>Drake</hi> or <hi>Columbus</hi> to undertake this voiage, or any <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>alus</hi> to invent a conveyance through the aire. However, I doubt not but that time who is ſtill the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of new truths, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed unto us many things which our Anceſtours were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of, will alſo manifeſt to our poſterity, that which we now deſire, but cannot know. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. Quaſt. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Veniet tempus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Seneca) quo iſta quae nunc latent, in lucem dies extrahet, &amp; longioris aevi diligentia.</hi> Time will come when the indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of after ages ſhall bring ſuch things to light, as now lie hid in obſcurity. Arts are not yet come to their Solſtice, but the induſtry of future times aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted with the labours of their forefathers, may reach unto that height which wee could not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to. <hi>Veniet tempus quo poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri noſtri nos tam aperta neſciſſe</hi>
                  <pb n="208" facs="tcp:28034:110"/> 
                  <hi>mirentur.</hi> As wee now won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the blindneſſe of our Anceſtors, who were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to diſcerne ſuch things as ſeeme plaine and obvious unto us. So will our poſterity ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire our ignorance in as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous matters. <hi>Keplar</hi> doubts not, but that as ſoone as the art of flying is found out, ſome of their Nation will make one of the firſt colonies that ſhall inhabite that other world. But I leave this and the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures to the fancie of the reader; Deſiring now to finiſh this Diſcourſe, wherein I have in ſome meaſure proved what at the firſt I promiſed, a world in the Moone. However, I am not ſo reſolute in this, that I thinke tis neceſſary there muſt be one, but my opinion is, that tis poſſible there may be, and tis probable there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther habitable world in that Planet. And this was that I
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:28034:110"/> undertooke to prove. In the purſuit whereof, if I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed much weakneſſe or indiſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; I ſhall willingly ſubmit my ſelfe to the reaſon and cenſure of the more judicious.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:28034:111"/>
            <head>The Propoſitions that are proved in this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <list>
               <label>
                  <hi>Propoſition</hi> 1.</label>
               <item>That the ſtrangeneſſe of this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is no ſufficient reaſon why it ſhould be rejected, becauſe other certaine truths have beene formerly eſteemed ridiculous, and great abſurdities entertayned by common conſent. <hi>By way of Preface.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 2.</label>
               <item>That a plurality of worlds do's not contradict any principle of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or faith.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:28034:111"/> 
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 3.</label>
               <item>That the heavens doe not conſiſt of any ſuch pure matter which can priviledge them from the like change and corruption, as theſe inferiour bodies are liable unto.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 4.</label>
               <item>That the Moone is a ſolid, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, opacous body.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 5.</label>
               <item>That the Moone hath not any light of her owne.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 6.</label>
               <item>That there is a world in the Moone, hath beene the direct opinion of many ancient, with ſome moderne Mathematicians, and may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably be deduced from the tenents of others.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:28034:112"/> 
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 7.</label>
               <item>That thoſe ſpots and brighter parts which by our ſight may bee di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in the Moone, doe ſhew the difference betwixt the Sea and Land in that other World.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 8.</label>
               <item>That the ſpots repreſent the Sea, and the brighter parts the Land.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 9.</label>
               <item>That there are high Mountaines, deepe vallies, and ſpacious plaines in the body of the Moone.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 10.</label>
               <item>That there is an Atmo-ſphaera, or an orbe of groſſe vaporous aire, immediately encompaſſing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the Moone.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:28034:112"/> 
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 11.</label>
               <item>That as their world is our Moone, ſo our world is their Moone.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 12.</label>
               <item>That tis probable there may bee ſuch Meteors belonging to that world in the Moone, as there are with us.</item>
               <label>
                  <hi>Prop.</hi> 13.</label>
               <item>That tis probable there may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants in this other World, but of what kinde they are is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
